<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The baptized Turk, or, A narrative of the happy conversion of Signior Rigep Dandulo, the onely son of a silk merchant in the Isle of Tzio, from the delusions of that great impostor Mahomet, unto the Christian religion and of his admission unto baptism by Mr. Gunning at Excester-house Chappel the 8th of Novemb., 1657 / drawn up by Tho. Warmstry.</title>
            <author>Warmstry, Thomas, 1610-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67626</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W880</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38490</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17512871</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17512871</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106523</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67626)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106523)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1107:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The baptized Turk, or, A narrative of the happy conversion of Signior Rigep Dandulo, the onely son of a silk merchant in the Isle of Tzio, from the delusions of that great impostor Mahomet, unto the Christian religion and of his admission unto baptism by Mr. Gunning at Excester-house Chappel the 8th of Novemb., 1657 / drawn up by Tho. Warmstry.</title>
                  <author>Warmstry, Thomas, 1610-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 150 [i.e. 158] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Williams, T. Garthwait ... and Henry Marsh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 97-158 misprinted 89-150.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian converts from Islam.</term>
               <term>Anglican converts.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106523:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106523:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Baptized Turk, OR A NARRATIVE Of the happy Converſion of Signior <hi>Rigep Dandulo,</hi> THE Onely Son of a Silk Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant in the Iſle of TZIO, from the Deluſions of that great Impoſtor <hi>Mahomet,</hi> unto the Chriſtian Religion: AND Of his Admiſſion unto Baptiſm by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. GUNNING at <hi>Exceſter-houſe</hi> Chappel the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1657.</p>
            <p>Drawn up by <hi>THO. WARMSTRY,</hi> D.D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 68.31.</hi>
               </bibl>—The Morians Land ſhall ſoon ſtretch out her hands to God.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Williams, T. Garthwait</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, and <hi>Henry Marſh</hi> at the Princes Arms at the lower end of <hi>Chancery-lane</hi> near the inner-Temple-gate in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106523:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106523:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable The Counteſs of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> The Honorable The Lord <hi>Gorge,</hi> And the Worſhipful <hi>Philip Warwick</hi> Eſq; Witneſſes at the Baptiſm of Signior DANDULO the Convert.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable, Honorable and Worſhipful,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Rue Honor is the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of Vertue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and where it hath its juſt deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and place, it is a ſhadow of that ſacred combination of Greatneſs and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb facs="tcp:106523:3"/>which are originally conjoyned, and even the ſame in God himſelf, and which ſhould never be ſeparated in the Creatures; indeed all true Greatneſs is the iſſue of Goodneſs, if it be rightly begotten, and then like a good Childe it is ordained to be the Nurſe of its own Mother, it being diſpenſed by God unto the Sons and Daughters of men, to be an advantage and encouragement, as well as an engagement unto ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, honourable and generous un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings. Of which, however the blear-eyed and doating world is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, there are none ſo truly and eminently glorious as thoſe that are converſant in Religion and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, which as it is the higheſt end that God did, or could aim at in the creation of Man; ſo it muſt therefore needs be the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt eminency and perfection, that the generations of men are capable of; for every thing is by ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:106523:3"/>more excellent, by how much the more it is advanced towards the ſcope and deſign of its being, and draweth nearer (if we may ſo ſpeak where there is no compariſon or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to be found) unto him who is the ſum of all that perfection which is in the accumulation of all Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Goodneſs together; and truly earthly Honor is then in its increment and exaltation, when it is made the ornament of Religion and Godlineſs, or rather is adorned by it. When the rayes of Eminency of Birth, Place or Reputation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God ſhines upon perſons of Dignity and Honor, reflect back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in holy gleams of heavenly love to God, and holy beams of il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration upon his Worſhip and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and when they raiſe that holy return unto God that was in <hi>Davids</hi> ſoul at the dedication of his houſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.1. <hi>I will extol thee, O Lord, becauſe thou haſt lifted me up, and
<pb facs="tcp:106523:4"/>not made my foes to triumph over me:</hi> And certainly this is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt end for which God beſtows Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor upon the greateſt men, that they may be the more conſpicuous, and the more exemplary in the ſervice and adoration of God, and not be as too many in our Age and Nation, like unthankful clouds, obſcuring the Sun that raiſed them; or like the Moon in the Dragons Tail eclipſing that glory from whence ſhe receiveth all her light. It is therefore the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt advancement that you can give to your State and Dignity to let it ſhine in the Sanctuary of the Lord, that you may by your holy and eminent patterns help to undeceive the beſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted World, that looks upon Offices of Religion as if they were a buſineſs fit onely for thoſe that are of a low condition; that you may make them know that Crowns and Diadems, and Robes of Honor ate never ſo reſplendent as when they are caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:106523:4"/>the Throne of the great God: How amiable was it to ſee you of late as ſo many Stars in your ſeveral ſphears and degrees of Glory, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as a propitious conſtellation at the new birth of this our Convert, when you were Witneſſes at his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm! and I hope you were orient and aſcendent at that hour, and then I need not doubt but you had your happy influence, as well in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement of a ſpiritual bleſſing upon his Soul, as you honorable Madam have been ſpecial and noble in taking care for his ſupportance and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement. And I wiſh you may never want the milk of the divine breaſt of that God unto whoſe new-born Child you are become ſo bountiful a Nurſe; wherein you have provided not onely for him, but for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Chriſtian, yea of the poor Engliſh Church, and for the encouragement of others to come in to the embracement of Gods Truth,
<pb facs="tcp:106523:5"/>in the entire reliance upon the divine mercy, which I wiſh you may ſee ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual in a happy confluence of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny multitudes unto the Goſpel of Chriſt, to the advancing of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of your piety from his hand whoſe abundant bleſſing I wiſh upon you all, who am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honoured Madam, Noble Lord, Worthy Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your humble Servant in Chriſt Jeſus, THO. WARMSTRY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:106523:5"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <head type="sub">Giving an Account of the laſt Conference betwixt Mr. <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> and Signior <hi>Dandulo.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>After theſe words, pag. 96. line 23.</hi> After our departure it pleaſed God to ſend reverend Mr. <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> who after ſome ſtrugglings obtained from him at length (as if ſome violent beam of light and grace had broken in upon his ſoul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not onely a conſent to be baptiſed, but an earneſt deſire that it might be done without delay, ſaying, <hi>Let it be done to morrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="dialogue">
               <p>THat the Reader may be ſatisfied, who will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably deſire to know what that laſt Diſcourſe was betwixt Mr. <hi>Gunning</hi> and Signior <hi>Dandulo,</hi> which obtained from him his conſent to be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, Dr. <hi>Warmſtry</hi> by Letter intreated Mr <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> that he would be pleaſed to ſet down that laſt Diſcourſe, which at Dr. <hi>Warmſtry's</hi> requeſt, Mr. <hi>Gunning</hi> hath done in the following account.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. Gunning.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ignior,</hi> You may remember that when I was with you before, I told you that we muſt found our diſcourſe concerning our two different Religions on that wherein we both are agreed concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religion; which was this; That the <hi>Light of Nature</hi> and <hi>Right Reaſon</hi> common to us both, hath confeſſedly taught us both, that one onely true God is to be worſhipped, the Maker, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver,
<pb facs="tcp:106523:6"/>Governor, and Judge of the world, and that the Dictates of Right Reaſon and of the Law of Nature are the Laws of that One God, in obedience whereto, to ſerve that One God true Religion. Now whatever Religion ſupe adds more then this, which the light of Nature teacheth, pretending <hi>ſupernatural Revelation</hi> for its perfecting, clearing, and repairing what by ſin is become maimed, corrupt and obliterate, in the dim light of Nature which needeth medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, (as both Chriſtianity and Turciſm do ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peradd) muſt either bring proofs of ſuch their ſuperaddition, &amp; pretended ſupernatural Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, or muſt juſtly be ſuſpected of Impoſture. The proof of a ſupernatural Revelation and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion made by Jeſus Chriſt to the world, I having inſtantly offered you, you tell me it is unneceſſary for that your own Religion doth confeſs and witneſs that already, and if Jeſus Chriſt were not a true Prophet come from God, Mahomet muſt confeſs himſelf a falſe Prophet. It remains therefore, as I told you, and now this ſecond time expect your deliberate Anſwer, <hi>viz.</hi> That you bring ſome proof that Mahomet hath received from God any ſuch ſupernatural Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation for the founding of his new Religion.</p>
                  <p>I askt you if it can be well proved concerning any <hi>ſupernatural Miracles</hi> which he wrought, or any Prophecy concerning him that had been known or affirmed by any, before his affirming it himſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sig. Dandulo.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I told you that</hi> Chriſt Jeſus <hi>himſelf did foretell of</hi> Mahomet <hi>to come.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
                  <p>If this can be proved, you ſay well and beleive well, for I having proved the Truth of Chriſtianity, from the Confeſſion of Mahometa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm; if you can prove the Religion of Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met
<pb facs="tcp:106523:6"/>from the Prediction of Chriſt, then you have alſo the confeſſion of Chriſtianity: But now I Convene your Conſcience, and require you before Chriſt Jeſus, whom you call <hi>The Spirit of the living God,</hi> and we <hi>the Word and Son of the living God,</hi> to whoſe <hi>Prediction</hi> you now appeal, and to which we Chriſtians muſt certainly be moſt obliged and willing to ſtand, to alledge and aſſign if you can through all that ſix hundred years that paſt 'twixt Chriſt and Mahomets time, any <hi>words</hi> witneſſed to have come from Jeſus Chriſt by any Diſciple of his, or any deriving from them, or any <hi>Book</hi> extant before Mahomets birth written by any of the followers of Jeſus Chriſt, or by Jeſus Chriſt himſelf; or thirdly, any <hi>Company</hi> or <hi>communion of men</hi> that profeſt Religion in Jeſus Chriſt, who lived in that ſix hundred years 'twixt Chriſt and Mahomet, that ever witneſſed that any ſuch prediction or promiſe was made by Jeſus Chriſt concerning Mahomet, or held any ſuch <hi>Tradition</hi> amongſt them. If you are able to name any, let us hear the Author of ſuch words or Books, or ſuch company or communion of men, where or when they lived, or who ever heard of them. In ſum, ſhew any thing of <hi>Christ</hi>'s or <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſpeaking concerning Mahomet before Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets firſt ſaying it of himſelf. Or elſe if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be ſhewed, then tell me what could an Impoſtor have done other then Mahomet hath done in this? <hi>viz.</hi> either himſelf onely to witneſs of himſelf without doing any <hi>ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Miracles,</hi> which might bear witneſs to him, or to <hi>alleadge a witneſs</hi> for himſelf, which none ever heard ſpeak, nor ever ſaid that he ſo witneſs'd, except and before himſelf. If to this you are ſtill unable to reply any thing, we are
<pb facs="tcp:106523:7"/>both willing to put our ſelves upon that iſſue for the tryal of our grounds of our beleiving in Chriſt, which Jeſus Chriſt himſelf offered his Adverſaries for the proof of his Doctrine.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Joh. 10.25.</note> 
                     <hi>The works that I do, they bear witneſs of me.</hi>
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">Joh. 10.37, 38.</note> 
                     <hi>If I do not the works of my Father beleive me not; but if I do, though you beleeve not me, beleeve the works.</hi>
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">Joh. 15.24.</note> And in another place, <hi>if I had not done among them the works which none other did, they had not had ſin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſecondly, We are ready to alledge num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſs Volumes written by the followers of Jeſus Chriſt within that ſix hundred years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſts Aſcenſion, and Mahomets com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and living Societies of Chriſtian Profeſſors throughout the World, and throughout thoſe ſix. Ages which witneſſed to certain Books as containing the Doctrines, and Inſtitutions, and Precepts, and Predictions made by Jeſus Chriſt; in all which Books, according to any Copies in any Language extant within thoſe 600 years, there is not any word of mention concerning ſuch a Prophet as Mahomet to come, nor any Tradition ever heard of amongſt thoſe Chriſtians concerning ſuch a Prophet to come: Whereas we fetch our witneſs concerning the Propheſies of the coming of Jeſus Chriſt from Books writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten many Ages before Chriſts coming, which our bittereſt Adverſaries the Jews keep, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, and own as <hi>the Oracles of God,</hi> confirmed to be ſuch at firſt by ſupernatural miracles; and which Books our other Adverſaries the <hi>Pagans</hi> had read and acknowledged to be extant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the coming of Chriſt. Indeed, whereas Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt <hi>propheſied</hi> that after his departure, <hi>he would, ſend the Holy Ghoſt the Paraclete to lead his Apoſtles into all truth,</hi> and ſo it muſt needs
<pb facs="tcp:106523:7"/>be whilſt the Apoſtles were yet alive, he having promiſed it to them. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> firſt about the fortieth year of Chriſt, gave out him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be that <hi>promiſed Holy Ghoſt, or Paraclete among the Gentiles;</hi> and about the year 220. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt<note n="(d)" place="margin">Epiph. Haereſ. <hi>48</hi> Aug. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. <hi>20.86.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Montanus</hi> pretended that he was <hi>that Paraclete,</hi> and that Jeſus Chriſt had prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied of him; and about the year 278 after Chriſt<note n="(e)" place="margin">Epiph. Haereſ. <hi>66.</hi> Aug. Haereſ. <hi>46.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Manes</hi> or <hi>Manicheus</hi> gave out himſelf to be <hi>that Paraclete,</hi> and that Jeſus Chriſt had propheſied of him; all which could ſhew in the Books of Jeſus Chriſt <hi>a Paraclete</hi> foretold ſhould come, but no reaſon of their blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous affirmation, that they were <hi>that Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clete:</hi> Then, 600 years after Chriſt <hi>Mahomet,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends that Jeſus Chriſt had propheſied of him as a great Prophet that ſhould come into the world, but he not able ſo much as to ſhew any ſuch Propheſie of any Prophet; now this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture being ſo groſs, what can your Conſcience have to anſwer before God, to follow longer, and to tranſmit to poſterity by your adhaeſion, ſuch a couſenage in ſo great a matter, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Religion of the moſt High God, and the eternal woe or welfare of your own and others immortal Souls, contrary to the Religion both that which the light of Nature and right Reaſon, I told you taught us both, and that which he whom you call <hi>the Spirit of God,</hi> and we call <hi>the Word of God</hi> (by and from whom all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, if Prophets of God, muſt ſpeak) hath taught the whole world; and which Prophets cannot ſpeak contrary one to another, nor to the Spirit of God, by whoſe inſpiration they are prophets, nor to the Word of God who ſpeaks by them.</p>
                  <p>Sir, I pray tell me, need I further to prove to
<pb facs="tcp:106523:8"/>you Chriſtianity, or need I further explain to you the <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> then has been done?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sig. D.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No, They are true.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
                  <p>If ſo you beleive, will you be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed into that Faith?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sig. D.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How think you I can do that without danger to my life? except I ſhould reſolve never to ſee more my Country, and Parents, and Friends, and all that is in this world dear unto me?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
                  <p>I know well and conſider that you cannot, without ſuffering that loſs for Chriſt his ſake, and yet for your own ſake alſo; for you muſt remember that we took the riſe of our diſcourſe from what we were both agreed in, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Light of Nature</hi> and <hi>Right Reaſon,</hi> which teacheth us, and hath taught many Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Philoſophers, that the eternal concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our immortal Souls after this life, is to be infinitely preferred before any ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations of ſuch worldly and temporary loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and that the one true living God, which Right Reaſon teaches is the Author of all good things Temporal and Eternal, and All-ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to make good to us any thing we loſe for his ſake, and is moſt certainly the rewarder of them that ſeek out the true Religion, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly follow it when they finde it. Alſo when you began any diſcourſe about Religion, we took it for granted on both ſides, that they are moſt unworthy to hear or make any ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, who are not reſolved to adhere to the Truth, whatever worldly inconvenience come thereby. Alſo I now inform you of one part of the Revelation made by Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>there is no man who forſakes Father, or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or Brethren, or Siſters, or Houſes, or Lands
<pb facs="tcp:106523:8"/>for his ſake and the Goſpels, but he ſhall receive in this world an hundred fold</hi> (however in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al benedictions and conſolations) <hi>with perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and in the world to come everlaſting life. Having food and rayment</hi> we are bid <hi>therewith to be content;</hi> and that he hath promiſed to our prayers and honeſt endeavors, having left us this aſſurance, that the <hi>godlineſs</hi> of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion <hi>hath the promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi> But tell me Signior, is it not everlaſting life, and the true Religion, which leads thereto, concerning which you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to diſcourſe with me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sig D.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, that, that only is conſiderable, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever becomes of my Body. But tell me, I pray Sir, may I not hold this Religion which you have taught me without being baptized, which is the onely thing will bring danger to me from my Country-men?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, you muſt, as believe, ſo alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Faith of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſet to your ſeal that this is the True Religion, and receive the ſeal of Gods Covenant, and not be aſhamed to renounce that ſhameful Impoſture of Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and own the Faith of the Lord of Glory Jeſus Chriſt, whom we teach and preach unto you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sig. D.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But where is that in your Books requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that I muſt needs be Baptized?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
                  <p>Hear me read out of that Book of God I pray you.<note n="(f)" place="margin">Joh. 3.6, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Amen, Amen, I ſay unto thee, except any one be born of Water and of the Spirit he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God; that which is born of the fleſh is fleſh, and that which is born of the Spirit is Spirit.</hi>
                     <note n="(g)" place="margin">Mark. 16.15, 16</note> And another place, <hi>Go ye into all the world and preach the Goſpel to every creature; He that believes and is
<pb facs="tcp:106523:9"/>baptized ſhall be ſaved, he that believes not ſhall be damned,</hi>
                     <note n="(h)" place="margin">A &amp;. 22.16.</note> And in another place, <hi>Ariſe and be baptized, and waſh away thy ſins, calling on the name of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sig. D.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To morrow, to morrow I will be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, our Religion and Diſcipline per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits not that haſtineſs in this weighty matter, you muſt firſt be more fully inſtructed in the neceſſary works of Repentance, and Articles of Faith and Vows to be made in your Baptiſm, all which we will immediately go about, and within convenient time, through the mercy of God, you ſhall receive holy Baptiſm.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sig. D.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But what if I ſhould die in the mean time of this deferring?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
                  <p>God will accept your preſent will, and deſires for that deed, which it is his will ſhould not be performed, but upon due prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; in the mean time, let us humbly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs our ſelves to prayers unto God through Jeſus Chriſt, and call upon him on whom you have believed, that he will fit you for Baptiſm, by perfecting in you true Repentance, and a lively faith, and vouchſafe you remiſſion of all your ſins, and renewing of the Holy Ghoſt in the Laver of holy Baptiſm.</p>
               </sp>
               <closer>
                  <signed>PETER G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NNING.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106523:9"/>
            <head>THE Happy <hi>CONVERT,</hi> OR THE <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RK</hi> Baptiſed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD having been pleaſed of his great goodneſs to give a bleſſing unto the poor endeavors that have been uſed for the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a Soul from the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and deluſions of the Mahumetan Infidelity, to the holy Truth of the ſaving Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a comfortable acceſs hath been made unto the afflicted Church of <hi>England;</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the diſcouragements that are upon ſuch deſigns in theſe evil times; I ſuppoſe it may be conducible to the glory of God, and to the comfort of his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful people, that deſire the advancement of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106523:10"/>the Kingdom of Chriſt Jeſus, and for the ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of others to the employment of their labours for the bringing home of ſuch, and others that are miſled, unto the Fold of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that there may be ſome account given unto the people of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that ſome publick Record may be left unto Poſterity of the gracious diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Almighty in this matter. I have therefore thought good to ſet forth this brief declaration thereof, in hope that it will be no unacceptable ſervice to God and his people.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Name, Linage, and Country of this Convert.</head>
               <p>THe name of this perſon whom God hath thus graciouſly brought home unto his Church, was before his Baptiſm <hi>Rigep,</hi> or in our Language <hi>Joſeph Dandulo,</hi> derived by ſix or ſeven Generations or Deſcents from a noble Family of the <hi>Danduli</hi> of <hi>Venice.</hi> Of this Name and Family I find divers in the Catalogue of <hi>Grimſtone,</hi> who have been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to the great Dignity of the Dukedom of that famous and antient Common-wealth.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106523:10"/>
               <p>The firſt, <hi>Henry D' Andule,</hi> in whoſe time <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was taken, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of the Eaſt gained, wherein he aſſiſted the Princes and Barons of the French. This <hi>Henry D' Andule</hi> died General of all the Chriſtian Armie.</p>
               <p>Another <hi>Dandule</hi> choſen in his abſence, in whoſe time the City was afflicted with Water and Earthquakes, he made war in <hi>Iſtria</hi> againſt the Patriarch of <hi>Aquileia,</hi> and the Count <hi>Caritia;</hi> at the inſtance of Pope <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas,</hi> he ſuccoured with Twenty five Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Tripoly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third, <hi>Francis D' Aridule,</hi> by whoſe interceſſion (caſting himſelf at the feet of the Pope with a chain of iron about his neck) the Excommunication of the Pope had been formerly taken off from <hi>Venice.</hi> In the time of his Dukedom, they of <hi>Pola</hi> and <hi>Valeſe</hi> ſubmitted themſelves to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth; <hi>Padua</hi> was taken; he was of the League of the Chriſtian Princes againſt the Turk; and in his time there were Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Ambaſſadors at once in <hi>Venice;</hi> he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned ten years and ten moneths.</p>
               <p>The fourth, <hi>Andrew D' Andule,</hi> who cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the dearth to ceaſe by bringing Corn from <hi>Sicily,</hi> he obtained of the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> free Navigation into <hi>Egypt. Zura</hi> having
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106523:11"/>rebelled the ſeventh time was recovered; War was made againſt the <hi>Genuois,</hi> and the City was troubled with Earthquakes and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence; he governed about twelve years</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe that enjoyed the excellency of the Dukedom, there is mention alſo of one <hi>Matthew Dandalo,</hi> who was ſent Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador, together with <hi>Nicholas de Ponte,</hi> from <hi>Hierom Prioli</hi> then Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> to the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From this noble Stock of the Venetian Commonwealth, was this our Convert, it ſeemeth, ſprung; ſo that he is derived, as we ſee from Chriſtian Anceſtors. The corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of whoſe blood have now, (as I may ſo ſpeak) been reſtored and purified in him by the water of holy Baptiſm, which he hath now lately through Gods mercy received.</p>
               <p>Some of the braches of that generous Stock have been it ſeemeth tranſplanted (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably) in the various events of thoſe Wars which have been ſo frequent between the Turk and the Venetians, of whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this our welcome Chriſtian is at this time a ſilk Merchant of good Eſtate in the Iſland of <hi>Tzio,</hi> not far from <hi>Smyrna,</hi> a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Turk, but his Mother is a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, of the Greek Church; whoſe Chriſtian profeſſion, as it did inveſt him unto a juſt title unto Baptiſm, even in his infancy; for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106523:11"/>the unbeleeving Husband is ſanctified by the Wife, and therefore the Childe was holy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. ſo it may be, the prayers of this Chriſtian Mother, like the tears of <hi>Monica</hi> for her <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> have miniſtred unto the good providence of Almighty God, for the bringing home of this ſtraied ſheep unto the holy Fold of Chriſt Jeſus. This happy Convert her Son, was the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Divine Providence in many notable paſſages of his life hitherto, through which the Lord hath at laſt brought him to this happy period of his wandrings, and change of his Profeſſion, into the boſom of the perſecuted Engliſh Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of his Education, and Travails.</head>
               <p>IN his infancy he was bred up with his parents, but according to the way of the deluſions of his Father, whoſe authority prevailed againſt thepious inclinations and deſires of his Mother, which yet now at length God hath bleſſed with the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and with a ſucceſs even beyond her
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106523:12"/>deſires; having brought him into a more pure profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religion then that which ſhe embraceth; even in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that which is embraced by the old and Orthodox part of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> then which (I hope we may be allowed to ſay) there is none in the world that doth more ſoundly embrace the Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and is glorious even in the rubbiſh, the very ſtones and duſt of the ruins which ſhe is under, and whom God hath ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly owned even in this time of her trouble and contempt, by giving this extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary acceſs unto her Body.</p>
               <p>About the ſixth year of his age he was ſtoln away by the Moors, amongſt whom he lived for the ſpace of about Nine years, and in that time he viſited the great City of <hi>Grand Cairo</hi> in <hi>Egypt;</hi> the place where God was pleaſed to deliver his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of old, that he might bring them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the land of Canaan: And ſo God hath called even this his Son, his newly adopted Son from Egypt. The Moor with whom he lived had a great deſire to have detained him with him, and for an inducement thereunto offered him his Daughter. But God who had another and far more happy marriage in ſtore for him, would not ſuffer him to lay hold upon that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106523:12"/>bait, but made uſe of the natural deſire that he had to ſee his Parents and his Country, to bring him from thence, that at length he might arrive at a better Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, even a Heavenly one, which is the Church of God; and come home unto bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Parents, even God himſelf, and the Catholike Church. And ſo as <hi>Saul</hi> ſought his Fathers Aſſes, and found a Kingdom; he might by the deſire that he had unto a natural bleſſing, be ſet in the way to the obtaining a ſupernatural Inheritance.</p>
               <p>So that God that in his wiſe Providence ordereth all things and motions of the World to the advancement of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and for the good and ſalvation of his People; and that maketh Nature it ſelf ſerve the deſigns and purpoſes of his heavenly grace, drew this perſon from his Mooriſh entertainment by the cords of thoſe inclinations that were in him to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his friends, and his native Soil, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Fathers houſe, where he arrived back again at the age of about Fifteen years. But his long abſence having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed the hopes, and diſcharged the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of his Parents to ſee him again, he was become now nowhere a greater ſtranger then at home: The impreſſions of natural relation were in a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106523:13"/>worn out, and thoſe characters that were yet left almoſt ſtarved for want of that nouriſhment which they uſually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from the enterview of preſence, or entercourſe of intelligence; even theſe it ſeems were ſo far out-grown by him, that there could be little or no compliance found between the ſpecies or forms he left behind him in their minds, and the favour and garb wherein he returned unto them; ſo that when he came to his Mothers door, and renewed his claim unto the Womb that bare him, and to the Breſts that gave him ſuck, the Mother fulfilled the word of God by the Prophet, and had forgotten her own ſucking childe; ſhe was hardly brought to own him for her Son, though ſhe had no other childe of that ſex to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his room in her heart. For it is not to be omitted that he is the onely Son of his Parents; ſo that his retirement into the boſom of Gods Church, cannot reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, much leſs charitably, be looked upon as an earthly refuge, but as a gracious and heavenly choice, ſince he had ſo ſtrong an intereſt as is that of an onely Son, both in the affection and care of thoſe parents that were and are ſo well able to provide for him. And indeed though it be true, that it is the wonder of the Divine Mercy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106523:13"/>that the Lord is pleaſed not to refuſe the very rejections and refuſes of the world, and to take up thoſe whom their Fathers and Mothers forſake; To receive a poor returning Prodigal that is driven unto him by the diſappointment of the very trough and husks of the Swine, and take up even out-caſts into his fatherly boſom: And though the ſame moſt gracions God thinks good to make the unhoſpitableneſs and ill entertainment of the Relations and uſage of the World, a means to bring in many ſincere Converts into his Houſe and Family; yet it is ſuch an Argument of ſincerity, as may well advance both our confidence and joy in this our late received Fellow-Chriſtian, that he comes unto us upon more noble, generous, and free in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements, then the want of an intereſt in thoſe earthly friends, that were well able to maintain him in that profeſſion that he was in.</p>
               <p>Neither was he long ſhut out either from the doors or from the bowels of his rechallenged Parents; for although at the firſt he was not acknowledge, yet (as Mothers are curious ſpeculators of their Children,) ſhe had, it ſeems, laid up in her memory againſt this time of need a certain mark that ſhe had obſerved in the body
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106523:14"/>of her Childe, to which ſhe thought good to refer the trial of his plea for his reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution unto her Family and care; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſearch, having found that character upon him, ſhe and her Husband too, (as we may well imagin) received him with great joy into their mutual boſoms and embraces (as we uſe to do thoſe comforts that come beyond our expectations) even as if they had had him new born unto them, or had received him from the very grave of death; which muſt needs ſtir up great endearments in their hearts, and raiſe up great joy and ſolace in their ſouls, whilſt they might ſay in the litteral ſence, as the Prodigals Father did in the ſpiritual, <hi>It is meet that we ſhould rejoyce, for this our Son was loſt and is found, he was dead,</hi> as to our enjoyment or knowledge of him, <hi>and is alive again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this was the firſt remarkable return of our Convert from his Mooriſh pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage unto his Fathers houſe.</p>
               <p>But in this he was but his own <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> as it were. This was but the dark type and figure of that more bleſſed return that he hath now lately made unto his heavenly Father, and to his Mother the Church. I conceive I may well call this a return too, becauſe though he ſprang
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106523:14"/>immediately from a Turkiſh Father, yet he was not onely derived from Chriſtian An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, as is before declared, <hi>(and God hath mercy for thouſands)</hi> but he received his conception and birth in and from the Womb of a Chriſtian Mother; and ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſtles deciſion (who allotteth the Title not unto the ſtronger in reſpect of Nature, but unto the better principle in reſpect of Grace, or the Chriſtian profeſſion) he was born into the world an holy Childe, and in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of the Catholick Church of Chriſt; from whence, though he was raviſhed for a time by thoſe evil principles which his bad Education infuſed into him, yet the Lord hath now in mercy reſtored him thereunto.</p>
               <p>Yet he did not preſently attain unto this bleſſing, but was carried through divers other Providences unto that happy time and place to which God had reſerved him for the receiving of ſo great a mercy. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing received again into his Fathers Family about the age (as he relates) of 15 years, he there continued for ſome certain time: But after ſome years having both perſon and gifts to encourage him, and render him acceptable for the ſervice of the Wars, He was engaged in ſeveral Expeditions
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106523:15"/>againſt the Chriſtians, and was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf employed in that late Battel between the Turk and Venetian, and was a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and partner in that defeat which fell on the Mahumetans ſide; and by ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through part of the Sea unto the Land, eſcaped that deſtruction which ſo many others of the Mahumetans reciev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that defeat that befel the Turkiſh Army.</p>
               <p>And God made his deliverance a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py means of the eſcape of a poor Chriſtian Slave whom he met withal, delivered from his hard Maſter by that ſtorm. This poor Chriſtian he met with when he was got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to Land, and although he might have made good advantage unto himſelf by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning him again to his Maſter: Yet having received a command from his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be kind and merciful unto Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and that loving and ingenuous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition that appears to be in him, inclin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to compaſſionate one that had been under ſo great a miſery, he was will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to venture his own ſafety, in aſſiſting him to make his eſcape away.</p>
               <p>Another Chriſtian, (as it is averred) he redeemed at another time at the rate of fourty and ſix Dollars of which he want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the odd ſix in money to make up the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106523:15"/>ranſom of the poor Captive, he pawned his Garment to make it up; and ſurely as this compaſſion of his, whilſt yet a Turk, towards thoſe that were then ſo adverſe to him in their profeſſion, may ſhame here and will condemn hereafter that uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate bowelleſs cruelty that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans now exerciſe one towards another, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom every difference in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or practice, is not onely taken for a diſcharge of love, but an engagement unto hatred and cruelty, which may well make our and other Chriſtian Nations as red with bluſhing, as they are with the blood of one another: So we may well conceive, that God that loves all goodneſs, and every thing in every creature that beareth any reſemblance of himſelf, hath graciouſly rewarded the pitty and mercy of this (then) Mahumetan unto poor Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, by pouring out that flood of mercy and compaſſion upon him, in the illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his ſoul with his heavenly truth, and his ingrafting into the myſtical Body of Chriſt Jeſus, yet not of any merit, but of his free goodneſs.</p>
               <p>I think not fit to forget, (though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps I have not remembred it in its due place,) that whilſt he was converſant with his Parents at home, it being one of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106523:16"/>Mahumetan Laws, that all ſhall take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the ſtate of Marriage at the age of Twenty five years old at the furtheſt, one or both of his Parents propoſed a Wife unto him; The treaty whereof was even yet on foot, when he came lately out of thoſe parts, and good endearment of affection was entertained on both ſides, which yet he is now content to ſacrifice in the fire of that holy love which hath been ſince kindled in his breſt toward the Lord Jeſus and his holy Goſpel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Age, Stature, and Qualities of the Convert.</head>
               <p>HIS Age is now about Twenty four years, his Stature tall, his Body very ſlender, his colour ſomething ſwarthy, and of the die of thoſe Climates wherein he hath lived, his feature comely, and his deportment very loving and courteous, he is very temperate in his diet, ſober and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly in his converſation, of a chearful and ingenous diſpoſition, of extraordinary underſtanding and knowledge for one that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106523:16"/>hath been bred up in thoſe parts, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe people where Arts and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are under reſtraints and prohibitions; he is of a pregnant wit, and of good and elegant expreſſion, adorned with hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom rhetorical flowers and illuſtrations, he is one that diſlikes debauchery of life, and hath complained before his converſion, of miſcarriages of that kinde which he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in ſome that walk under the name of Chriſtians, particularly of ſome whom he met with at <hi>Wapping;</hi> which ſhould admoniſh both them and others that live in an irregular courſe of life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, to conſider ſeriouſly of the great diſhonor that they thereby do unto Chriſt and the profeſſion of the Goſpel, and the great danger that is upon them, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come anſwerable unto the dreadful judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, not only for their own ſouls whom they ruine by their wickedneſs, but of the ſouls of many others whom they may ruine by their ſcandals; whilſt they draw ſome into the like wickedneſs by their evil and contagious examples, and hinder others from embracing that truth, the profeſſion whereof they finde accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with ſuch vile debauchery of life and converſation; and ſo confirm them in their errors to the ruine of their ſouls which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106523:17"/>are like to be laid to their charge at the laſt day; God grant we may all lay this unto our hearts; for I am perſwaded the wickedneſs of Chriſtians at the laſt day, will be charged with the loſs and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the reſt of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the occaſion and motive of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt that we may make haſte unto the main Buſineſs, and ſet before you that bleſſed work which the Lord hath wrought upon this our Convert, to the praiſe of the glory of his grace:</p>
               <p>When he had for ſome time ſolaced him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the enjoyment of the comforts of his recovered Parents and their Family, and paſſed through ſome other varieties of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence both in War and Peace, being as it ſeems of too active a ſpirit to be ſhut up within the narrow bounds of his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-contentments; he took a journey to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> where he met with Mr. <hi>Lawrence,</hi> Son to the Lady <hi>Lawrence</hi> of <hi>Chelſey,</hi> with whom he fell into ſome acquaintance,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106523:17"/>whereby (though then it were little dreamt of) God made ſome preparations for that happy change that hath bin ſince wrought upon him, as will appear anon.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Smyrna</hi> he departed to <hi>Tunis,</hi> and from <hi>Tunis</hi> to <hi>Algier,</hi> where we ſhall finde a gracious experiment of Gods great goodneſs unto his people, and ſee how he makes all things work together for good, and for the advancement of thoſe gracious deſigns which he hath contrived in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Councels, for the bringing home of his loſt ſheep unto him, and for the ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and exaltation of the Kingdom of his Son; and how he cauſes even the publike intereſts of thoſe Princes and Nations of the world, and their Politick and civil concernments, (however excentrical they are in their purpoſes to his end) yet in their occurrences and events to concenter with thoſe his gracious determinations, and that in order to thoſe mercies which he intends to one particular foul; ſo watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and careful is God for the advantage and benefit of his people, that deſigns of ſeveral great Nations and Kingdoms, nay, of the buſineſs of the whole world ſhall be brought in to ſerve and miniſter unto that bleſſing which he entendeth to one ſingle Soul, rather then he ſhall fail of his mercy.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106523:18"/>
               <p>Whilſt he was at <hi>Algier,</hi> being through providence diſappointed of another inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded journey, there was a diſpatch of an Agent from thence into <hi>England,</hi> that God appointed to be his Convoy to waft him over not onely from that Turkiſh Region into this Nation, but alſo (as it hath proved in the happy ſucceſs, which is a good interpreter of Gods intendments, though not ſo good for a commentary up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Laws, nor for the diſcovery of his judgment of our actions) to convey him from the Turkiſh Religion into the boſom of the true and orthodox Chriſtian Church; his deſire to ſee this ſtrange Nation, that is now (upon very ſad terms, as we may well conjecture) become the noiſe and the wonder of the world, inclined him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with that opportunity, not knowing yet what God meant to do with him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and ſo hither he came: And that nothing might be wanting to the fulfilling of the gracious purpoſe of the Almighty, the foreſaid Mr. <hi>Lawrence,</hi> the Son of the Lady <hi>Lawrence</hi> of <hi>Chelſey,</hi> was ſent over about the ſame time to meet him here, by whom he was after ſome time brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Chelſey</hi> to the houſe of his worthy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, where he was kindly entertained, and in the time of his firſt continuance
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106523:18"/>there, I had a ſight of him in his Turkiſh Habit; but as yet God had not ſtired up my heart to attempt any thing upon him for his Converſion; neither indeed did I well know how to aſſault him, he being as yet a ſtranger to the Engliſh tongue, nor acquainted with the Latin, nor any but the vulgar Greek, the Arab, and the Franck, which is a kinde of a baſtard Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian; but in the time of his being there he had entered into ſome familiarity with Mr. <hi>Lawrence</hi> a Turkiſh Merchant, who married the Daughter of the Lady <hi>Lawrence</hi> before mentioned, who finding him, as he conceived, proper for ſome pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of his, prevailed with him to ſtay ſome longer time in <hi>England</hi> then he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have done, and ſo became the means of that bleſſed opportunity, that hath been ſince laid hold on, for his illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. A while after he came again to the Lady <hi>Lawrences</hi> of <hi>Chelſey,</hi> at whoſe houſe I happily found him when I came thither one evening to do thoſe obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which I owe unto that worthy Lady (by whoſe favour I enjoy an habitation as her Tenant in the Town of <hi>Chelſey</hi>) but little did I dream what work the Lord had there for me to begin; but God having brought me thither began to work not onely by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106523:19"/>inward inclinations in me to the undertaking of that buſineſs of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, but alſo by the encouragement and compliant deſires of the Lady her ſelf, and Mr. <hi>Shugborough</hi> who ſo journeth with her; ſo in much weakneſs, with the aſſiſtance of Mr. <hi>Lawrence</hi> the Merchant, before-mentioned, who was pleaſed to do the part of an Interpreter between me and this Convert, I made an entrance upon the Work of his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the method and manner of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</head>
               <p>VPon the firſt attempt I found him very averſe, and even ſtrongly and deſperately reſolved to venture himſelf upon that Religion which his Father had entertained, and derived unto him, though it ſhould coſt him his damnation; yet at the laſt he was brought into ſome doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was the true Religion, the Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan or the Chriſtian; and ſeemed to tend towards a kind of indifferency; and ſome
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106523:19"/>expreſſions, (as I remember) fell from him, intimating a deſire that God would direct him to the truth; and as ſuch a thought, where it is ſincere, I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſeldom or never returns without a bleſſing, unleſs we be wanting unto our ſelves, in the uſe or embracement of Gods offers: ſo it is an excellent beginning to a work of Wiſdom and Grace upon a Soul, for a man to be brought ſo far from his Errors, as <hi>bene dubitare</hi> to doubt well; for moſt men periſh in evil and unground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed confidences; when therefore I found that this breach was made in that evil For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs wherein he had ſtood, I thought good to make the work as ſure as I could; and therefore reſolving not to rely upon my own ſtrength, in a buſineſs of ſo great concernment, I made haſte to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and imparted the buſineſs and the progreſs that I had made, and the hopes that I had, unto reverend Mr. <hi>Thirſecroſs,</hi> earneſtly deſiring his aſſiſtance in a matter that might bring ſo much glory to God; at leaſt that we might do our endeavors, that we might not be anſwerable to God for the loſs of his ſoul; withal expreſſing ſome hopeful confidence of a comfortable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in the undertaking: He ſeeing my ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs ſeemed to conjecture that there
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106523:20"/>was ſome more then ordinary ſtirring of the Spirit in the matter, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf very ready to give aſſiſtance in the Work; adviſed me to an Interpreter, which we much wanted, <hi>viz.</hi> one Mr. <hi>Samois,</hi> who had been a Traveller in the Turkiſh parts, and ſo knew very well how to accoſt him in that Language which is uſually ſpoken amongſt them in thoſe Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories which is the Frank Language, or baſtard Italian. This Gentleman was but lately returned from his Travels to his Country, and ſince that return made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther happier then that, from the errors and Superſtitions of Popery to the true Chriſtian Catholick, Apoſtolick Religion, profeſſed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to which God brought him by the advice and inſtruction of his learned and worthy Kinſman Mr. <hi>Samois,</hi> lately Chaplain to my Lord of <hi>Elgin;</hi> and ſo as <hi>Andrew</hi> having found out Chriſt, brought his brother <hi>Simon</hi> unto him, &amp; as <hi>Philip</hi> found out <hi>Nathanael,</hi> ſo the Lord was pleaſed to honor him, who had been but now very lately converted from his own Errors and Superſtitions to the embracement of the Truth, by making him a very great and active inſtrument of the converſion of another, even of this our lately baptized Chriſtian from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetan
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106523:20"/>Deluſions and Blaſphemies to the holy Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>But to the farther and ſurer promotion of our deſigne, Mr. <hi>Thirſcroſs</hi> with my ſelf, thought good to engage that worthy and learned Divine Mr. <hi>Peter Guning,</hi> who hath ſhewed himſelf a very able and worthy Champion of Gods Truth and his Church, both againſt Papiſts and others, that he might employ his excellent abilities for the bringing of this work begun unto a happy Iſſue.</p>
               <p>The motion was no ſooner made, but readily embraced by him.</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe he with Mr. <hi>Samois</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſeth himſelf unto <hi>Chelſey,</hi> to the houſe of the Lady <hi>Laurence,</hi> who was pleaſed to give a very favourable and courteouſs entertainment to all that came about that holy buſineſs (which I hope will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned in many bleſſings upon her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.)</p>
               <p>Upon the firſt Diſcourſe that Mr. <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and my ſelf together had with him, wherein Mr. <hi>Guning</hi> took great and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all pains there was yet no concluſion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in him anſwerable to deſire</p>
               <p>But the Lord himſelf the night after, it ſeems, took him in hand, and ſeconded our endeavors, with a very
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106523:21"/>ſtrange and Wonderful dream, which the Convert himſelf related the next Morning, and ſeemed not a little affected with it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The Relation of a ſtrange Dream, that the Convert had, after ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe had with him, before his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</head>
               <p>The Dream was this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>HE thought he ſaw a Table, with a very fair Veſſel like a Baſon, ſtanding upon it, and two men ſtanding by it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And preſently after he dreamt that he was ſtanding by a ſtreame, wherein he had a great Deſire to waſh himſelf; but the Stream, was ſuch a filthy ſtincking puddle water, that he could not waſh himſelf in it: In this filthy ſtream he thought he ſaw a Hen lie dead with her head or neck cut, and that a woman came and took this dead Hen out of the puddle water, and when ſhe had ſet it down upon its leggs, it ran away alive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>After this as he was troubled, that he could not waſh himſelf in that filthy ſtream
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106523:21"/>that was then before him, he thought he ſaw upon the ſuddain a very fair full and clear chryſtal ſtream break forth of a certain place, which came with great force and guſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the filthy ſtream and drove it clear away, and preſented it ſelf in the place of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Into this pure ſtream he entred, (though with ſome fearfulneſs at the firſt) and but by Degrees, waſhed himſelf in it, and ſwam over it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When he was gotten over the ſtream, and now as it ſeemed at ſome diſtance from it, he began to be very thirſty, and knew not how to get water to drink: But in this his neceſſity, there fell a ſhowre from Heaven, which when he ſaw he betook himſelf unto a poor houſe and knockt at the door; upon that a woman came out unto him, who upon requeſt, gave him a little diſh, with which he took ſome of the heavenly ſhowre that fell, and therewith quenched his thirſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:106523:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> An occaſional Diſcourſe concerning Dreams.</head>
               <p>THE Relation of this Dream raiſed ſome hope in us, that God had been pleaſed to own and ſecond our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours; So great compliance was then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween it and the holy deſigne we had in hand, which God was pleaſed as it ſeems to act over in the <hi>praeludium</hi> of this Dream, as afterwards he brought it to paſs in a waking performance; And indeed though many and moſt Dreams may go for the idle and impertinent iſſues of the wandring and extravagant fantaſies of men, and of the impreſſions which they receive either from predominant humors in the body, or vein, and evill affections in the mind, or from the repreſentations that are made in the time of ſleep, by the ſubtile operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of wicked Spirits; and ſo are either not to be much regarded, or elſe to be thought upon with humiliation and ſorrow, as thoſe Evidences and fruits which break forth in our very ſleeps, of our corrupt, vain, and ſinfull inclinations; yet ſome of them are of ſuch excellent harmony in their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106523:22"/>frame and Method, and have ſuch a ſtamp of ſobriety and holineſs upon them in their deſign and drift, that they ought not to be ſlightly paſſed over or forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, but to be diligently weighed and thought upon, that we may receive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and admonitions from them; eſpecially ſince we find t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t this hath been one way whereby God hath been pleaſed in very eminent maner, to make known his holy will and pleaſure to his people, and to admoniſh and direct them, both for the avoiding that which is Evill, and for the purſuance and embracement of that which is good and profitable unto them, and well pleaſing unto him; as is manifeſt in the notable and weighty Dreams record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Scriptures, as of <hi>Abimelech,</hi> Gen. 20. The Dream of <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 28. of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> Gen. 37. of <hi>Pharoah,</hi> Gen. 41. of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> Daniel 2. Daniel 4. of <hi>Daniel,</hi> Daniel 7. ſee Daniel. 8. &amp;c. Of the man of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Judges 7.13. of <hi>Solomon</hi> 1 Kings 3.5.15. of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> the husband of the Mother of Chriſt, Matth. 2.12.22. And that this is a way wherein God hath heretofore promiſed to manifeſt himſelf unto his people, you may learn by that which is written, <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Job</hi> 33.15. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.28. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.17. Nor
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106523:23"/>dare I condemn that which is ſaid to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by <hi>Antoninus</hi> that famous Emperor concerning cures by Dreams,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſaub.</hi> of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſ. <hi>ch.</hi> 5</note> 
                  <hi>not only</hi> (ſaith a learned Writter of our Church) <hi>approved unto himſelf by his own, but unto others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by frequent experience. Galen</hi> is ſaid of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to have had a Dream <hi>to write ſuch or ſuch a Book, to go, or forbear ſuch a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney;</hi> which puts me in mind of that which befell St. <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 16.9. unto whom <hi>a man of Macedonia appeared in a Viſion or Dream by night, and prayed him, ſaying, Come over into Macedonea and help us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccleſiastical Hiſtory,</hi> and other Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are left us of the various and wonderful paſſages of the world, afford us many and frequent examples of very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable things of this nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, when he was upon an Expedition againſt <hi>Tyre,</hi> thought in his Dream that he ſaw a <hi>Satyre,</hi> which upon conſultation had, this Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Tyre is thine;</hi> The very ſyllables of the name of that Monſter which he thought he ſaw, importing in their ſignification the Victory that he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; and the Succeſs was anſwerable thereunto.</p>
               <p>Another Dream of his is more famous and remarkable, as that which <hi>God</hi> ſeemeth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106523:23"/>to have made uſe of as an inſtrument of great and gracious Providence; and it was this: He thought he ſaw in a Dream or Viſion, the form of a man preſenting it ſelf unto him in rich and awful Attire, even thoſe very Robes which were uſed by <hi>Gods</hi> appointment by the <hi>High Prieſt</hi> of the <hi>Jews;</hi> and ſhortly afterwards, as he was riding toward <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he met <hi>Jadus</hi> in a Habit directly anſwerable to his Dream, which ſtruck ſuch an awful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into him, that he lighted from his Steed or Chariot, and did him great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, and by this means his fury was diverted from the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is related of <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">V. Plut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vita Caeſar. &amp; Valer. Maxim. l. <hi>1.</hi> c <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> that the night before his deſtruction he dreamed that he was placed by the Throne of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> and that by and by after he was tumbled down out of Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Simonides</hi> having exerciſed his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and mercy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Stro-zio de ſpirit. &amp; incan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat.</note> in burying of a dead man, and being afterwards determined to take a journey by Sea, thought he ſaw the ſame dead man whom he had buried, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing unto him, and admoniſhing him <hi>to forbear that Voyage,</hi> declaring unto him that if he ſhould undertake it, <hi>he ſhould miſcarry therein, and loſe his life.</hi> He took this admonition, and ſo eſcaped that ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106523:24"/>whereby all that went periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>The Mother of <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baldwin. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> de caſ. conſc. circ. divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationem</note> (as <hi>Baldwinus</hi> relateth out of the Hiſtory of his life) having petitioned <hi>God,</hi> in her prayers <hi>for a Sor,</hi> with a vow to deſtinate him to the holy ſervice of <hi>God,</hi> had it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to her in a Dream, <hi>That ſhe ſhould have a Son born of her,</hi> and had his <hi>Viſage</hi> preſented unto her, and <hi>his name</hi> declared in her Dream or Viſion.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> relateth in his Third Book of <hi>Confeſſions,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. l. <hi>3.</hi> Conf. Bald. ib.</note> that whilſt he was yet a <hi>Manichee,</hi> his Mother <hi>Monica</hi> had a Dream that ſhe was ſtanding upon a <hi>wooden Rule,</hi> and being very ſad, <hi>ſaw a glorious young man very joyful, and of a chearful countenance coming unto her, and that he asked her the cauſe of her ſadneſ; and when ſhe had declared that it was by reaſon of the ſorrow that ſhe had for her Son, who was then in the way of deſtruction; he bid her be of good chear, and wiſhed her to mark and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and that ſhe ſhould ſee her Son to be with her where ſhe was, and ſo ſhe ſaw her Son standing with her upon the ſame Rule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Anguſtine</hi> hath a ſtory of one <hi>Curmas</hi> that lived near unto <hi>Hippo</hi> where he was <hi>Biſhop,</hi> who in his ſleep thought
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106523:24"/>he ſaw himſelf <hi>Baptiſed</hi> by <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baldw. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> de caſ. conſ. circa ſpectra, caſ. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> and that afterwards he was <hi>led into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe,</hi> and as he was diſmiſſed from thence, he thought he heard a voyce ſaying unto him, <hi>Go and be baptiſed, if thou wilt be in this place of the bleſſed;</hi> and that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards being admoniſhed <hi>to be baptized by Auguſtine,</hi> and returning anſwer <hi>that that was already done</hi> (as his Dream had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preſented it to him) he that ſpake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in his Dream or Viſion replied thus, <hi>Go</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and be baptized indeed for that was but a Viſion;</hi> Whereupon he went to <hi>Hippo,</hi> and was amongſt others baptized by <hi>Auguſtine</hi> that knew nothing of the Viſion or Dream.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sozomen</hi> in the Sixth Book of his <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Hiſtory,</hi> and Second Chapter,<note place="margin">Sozom. hiſt. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> telleth us, that the death of <hi>Julian</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate, was fore-diſcovered to <hi>Didymus Alexandrinus</hi> in a Dream; and in the Fifth Chapter of the ſame Book, that the <hi>Tumults</hi> of the <hi>Arrians</hi> in the Church were diſcovered to <hi>Antonius</hi> in a Dream.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leſſius</hi> in his Book,<note place="margin">Leſſius de juſtitiâ, l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>45</hi> dub. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>De juſtitia &amp; jure caeteriſque virtutibus cardinalibus, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 45. <hi>dubit.</hi> 8. the title whereof is, <hi>Quouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que divinatio ex ſomnis ſit licita,</hi> makes mention of the Dream of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:106523:25"/>wherein he being yet a private man, thought he ſaw himſelf; crowned by <hi>Meleti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us a Biſhop,</hi> when as yet he had not thought of any ſtich thing, nor had any knowledg of the ſaid <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Theodor. Hiſt. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>6,</hi> &amp; <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> See <hi>Theodor. Hiſt. lib</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Leſſius</hi> alſo, in the ſame Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rem embers the Dream of St. <hi>Folicar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> who thought in his ſleep that <hi>his pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low was all on fire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leſſ. ubi ſupra.</note> whereby was ſignified the manner of his <hi>Martyrdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is alſo written in the life of <hi>Paraeus,</hi> that before the deſtruction of the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate,</hi> he ſaw in his Dream <hi>Heidleberg</hi> on fire.</p>
               <p>In the life of Sir <hi>Henry Wotton</hi> lately ſet forth, we have mention of two Dreams; one of <hi>Nicholas Wotton,</hi> Dean of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> Uncle to Sir <hi>Thomas Wotten;</hi> and the other of Sir <hi>Thomas Wotton</hi> himſelf,<note place="margin">The Life of Sir <hi>H, Wotton.</hi>
                  </note> Sir <hi>Henries</hi> Father.</p>
               <p>The firſt was this, <hi>Nicholas Wotton</hi> Dean of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> being Ambaſſador in <hi>France</hi> in the year, 1555. in the time of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> had a Dream wherein he was admoniſhed that <hi>Thomas Wotton</hi> his Nephew <hi>was inclined to be a party in ſuch a Project, which (if he were not ſpeedily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted) wonld turn to the loſs and ruine both of his life and Family.</hi> Whereupon he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106523:25"/>remembring the Dream of <hi>Monica</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> her Son; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that Almighty God hath even in latter times by a certain illumination of the Soul in ſleep, diſcovered in Dreams many things that humane wiſdom could not foreſee, reſolved to uſe ſome prudent remedy; to this end he wrote to the Queen and beſought her, <hi>That ſhe would cauſe his Nephew</hi> Tho. Wotton <hi>to be ſent for out of</hi> Kent <hi>and that the Lords of her Council might interrogate him in ſome ſuch feigned queſtions as might give a colour for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment into a favorable Priſon;</hi> declaring that <hi>he would acquaint her Majeſty with the true reaſon of his requeſt, when he ſhould next become ſo happy as to ſee and speak to her Majeſty.</hi> This was done according to his deſire, and <hi>Thomas Wotton</hi> committed to priſon. And by this means he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented from an engagement with <hi>Wyat</hi> and the Kentiſh Rebells; wherein (as he afterwards acknowledged to his Uncle, when he returned into <hi>England</hi>) he was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have been involved and ſo they both joyned in praiſing God for that admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which was given in the Dream for the prevention thereof.</p>
               <p>The other Dream was one that befel Sir <hi>Thomas Wotton</hi> himſelf, who (as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated) had many that did uſually prove
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106523:26"/>true, both in fore-telling things to come, and diſcovering things paſt: That which we now deſire to mention was this; Sir <hi>Thomas Wotton</hi> a little before his death dreamed, <hi>That the Treaſury of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of</hi> Oxford <hi>was robbed by Townſmen and poor Schollars, and that the number of them was Five;</hi> And being the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing to write unto his Son <hi>Henry</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then at <hi>Oxford</hi>) he gave him a ſlight notice thereof in a Poſtſcript of his Letter, which came to his Sons hands the very morning after the night in which the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery was committed (being ſent to him out of <hi>Kent</hi>) and when the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity</hi> were both in a perplexed inqueſt of the <hi>Theeves,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Wotton</hi> produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his Fathers Letter, and by it ſuch light was given that the Five <hi>Guilty perſons were diſcovered and apprehended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take one more,<note place="margin">Vita Cl. Salmaſii per Anto. Clement.</note> with which we will conclude our examples of remarkable Dreams; it is that of the learned and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Salmaſius,</hi> related in his Life, ſet forth by <hi>Antonius Clementius,</hi> before the volume of the Epiſtles of the ſaid <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salmaſius</hi> having a deſire to ſee <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Monuments that were there, and having provided himſelf for the journey,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106523:26"/>and entered himſelf into the company of ſome Merchants for that Voyage, the very night before he was to have taken it, was troubled with a terrible Dream, and <hi>thought he heard a voice, moſt earneſtly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading him from his purpoſe therein, and withal threatning him, that if he went on, he ſhould never return alive:</hi> Whereupon he deſiſted from his intended Travel, and ſo prevented that great danger that might very probably have befallen him amongſt thoſe people, from whom his great fame and learning would not likely have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to have been concealed, and whom he had ſo much provoked by his learned Labors in the maintenance of that truth which lies ſo oppoſite unto their evil inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and eſpecially by the care that he had taken for the publiſhing and poliſhing of <hi>Nilus</hi> and <hi>Barlaam,</hi> thoſe moſt eager E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Papal Monarchy.</p>
               <p>He that deſires to ſee more of this kind, may have recourſe for his further ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to <hi>Sarozzio de ſpiritibus &amp; incan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationibus, Wierus de praeſtigiis daemonum, Percerus de divinatione, Cicero de divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione,</hi> and others; as likewiſe to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Hiſtories of the World; amongſt the reſt, there is an Hiſtory that I have ſeen of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France,</hi> that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106523:27"/>makes mention of divers remarkable Dreams that uſhered in the violent death of that Great Prince, and amongſt the reſt one of them, as I remember, was this, That his Queen a little before his death dreamed, that <hi>all her Jewels were turned into Pearls;</hi> which are the uſual <hi>Emblems of Tears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe Examples, with many other that the Records of the times will afford us, may lead us ſafely unto this Concluſion; <hi>That God may and doth ſometimes admoniſh, not onely his own people, but others alſo,</hi> as <hi>Laban, Abimelech</hi> and <hi>Balaam</hi> by Dreams, and then it will eaſily follow, That <hi>all Dreams are not to be deſpiſed, but that ſome are ſeriouſly to be weighed, and made uſe of, as admonitions from God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:106523:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of the Nature of Dreams, their Cauſes and Kinds; and how far we may proceed in taking Obſervations and Admonitions from them, and what Rules are to be obſerved therein.</head>
               <p>HAving gained thus much, That <hi>there is ſome weight in ſome Dreams,</hi> and that as the Poet hath it, <hi>Somnia pondus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent,</hi> it will be of concernment for us not to leave this matter, until we have given ſome Directions concerning the Uſe that is to be made of them; the rather becauſe they are things very ſubject to be made the inſtruments of <hi>Deluſion</hi> by <hi>Satan,</hi> and of Superſtition by fooliſh, and weak, and wicked men. We need not go far, I think, from our own Age and Nation to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, That there is great miſcheif that proceeds from miſcarriages concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Dreams; whereby too many, it may be feared, have been and are at this day en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared both in errors of <hi>Judgment,</hi> and evill and vile <hi>Practiſes,</hi> in Affection and Converſation, contrary to the Truth and Holineſs of God: whereby our times are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106523:28"/>become the parallel of that evill <hi>Character</hi> that St. <hi>Jude</hi> gave of ſome wicked people in his own times,<note place="margin">Jude 8.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Likewiſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>theſe Drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers defile the fleſh, deſpiſe Dominion, and speak evil of Dignities:</hi> A glaſs wherein we may very viſibly behold the evill Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Dreamers and <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> of our days; They are called <hi>Dreamers</hi> (as <hi>Deodate</hi> conjectureth upon the place) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>they vented their own Dreams and Fancies inſtead of Gods Truth:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 23.25, to 28. <hi>Be a in Epiſt. Jud.</hi> Iſa. 56.10</note> See <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.25, to 28. <hi>Beza</hi> renders the word there <hi>Sopiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> and <hi>Grotius</hi> obſerveth that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Hebrew, <hi>Iſa</hi> 56.10. is tranſlated <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Greek; and it ſignifies (ſaith he) <hi>ſtulta imaginantes, it a ut ii qui ſomniant. Thoſe that imagine vain and fooliſh things, like them that dream.</hi> Indeed as Dreamers may be ſaid in ſome ſence to be awake in their ſleep; ſo our <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> are ſleeping Wakers, and their pretended <hi>Enthuſiaſms</hi> but waking dreams, the mad and wilde fancies of ſouls that are in the dead ſleep and ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſin; and though both Inſpirations and Dreams may be good where they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from <hi>a right principle,</hi> and are enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and uſed as they ought to be (as I have already ſhewed in that of Dreams)
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106523:28"/>yet they are very apt to be miſtaken, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they come very often in the dark, and not leſs apt to be abuſed to evill pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes: Inſomuch that (as a Learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath already obſerved of one of them) ſo I may be the bolder to ſay of both of them together,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cauſab.</hi> of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſm</note> that <hi>they have been made the colours and countenances of the moſt eminent miſchiefs that have been in the world;</hi> And therefore (as I ſhall be bold to ſay) that <hi>it is the part of a wiſe man to conſider his Dreams;</hi> ſo withall I ſhall ſay, that <hi>it is a point of good and of great Wiſdom to diſtinguiſh well of them, and to know how to uſe them aright.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is therefore a matter of concernment that we ſhould be rightly guided in that <hi>ſtrange converſation</hi> which we have with our ſelves, and <hi>spiritual natures in Dreams.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And at it is of concernment in it ſelf, ſo of the more becauſe it is a matter wherein I think I may ſay, we are moſt accountable to God for almoſt the third part of our lives. I mean all that time which is ſpent in <hi>ſleeping.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this <hi>concernment</hi> is attended with ſome <hi>difficulty,</hi> not onely becauſe it may ſeem to require ſome more then ordinary <hi>light</hi> to diſcover theſe matters of <hi>darkneſs,</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:106523:29"/>which uſually move in the obſcurities both of the <hi>greater</hi> and <hi>leſſer World;</hi> but becauſe it is that buſineſs of our life which is leaſt <hi>underſtood</hi> by us, and of which we are leaſt the <hi>Maſters,</hi> and therefore ſince, <hi>Ars eſt de difficili &amp; bono,</hi> The proper ſubject of Art is that which is uſeful and difficult. It requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſome <hi>skill</hi> to ſtate this <hi>queſtion</hi> aright.</p>
               <p>And firſt it will be requiſite to know what theſe <hi>Dreams</hi> are Methinks I may call them <hi>certain Meteors</hi> of the <hi>leſſer World,</hi> which appear in the humane night of the <hi>Microſm</hi> or <hi>little World</hi> of man.</p>
               <p>Some kind of ſtragglings that the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of life</hi> have with the <hi>chains of ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> under which they are bound, and as it were ſome <hi>breakings</hi> out from the <hi>Priſon of ſleep,</hi> ſome <hi>agitations</hi> of the mind with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſelf, raiſed either by ſome ſtrong im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions that the <hi>Memory</hi> hath received, which are ſo <hi>bright</hi> that they break through the <hi>cloud</hi> of <hi>ſleep,</hi> to the <hi>illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and ſtiring up of the <hi>Fancy</hi> or <hi>imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or by ſome earneſt or active <hi>affections</hi> that are in the <hi>Appetite</hi> or <hi>Iraeſcible Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of the Soul, which draw as it were the <hi>Pictures</hi> of thoſe things upon the table of the imagination, wherein they delight, or wherewith they are moved, clothed either with their <hi>hopes</hi> or <hi>fears,</hi> which make their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106523:29"/>Dreams either pleaſing or terrible, or by ſome either <hi>natural,</hi> or <hi>diſeaſed</hi> and <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental predominancy</hi> of ſome humors. The vapours whereof ariſing with ſome vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and thickneſs diſpoſe themſelves, as it were, into ſome kinde of <hi>figure</hi> like the <hi>clouds</hi> in the Heavens, according to their ſeveral tempers and complexions or by the influence of the <hi>Heavens;</hi> or temper of the <hi>Air,</hi> or by the operation of <hi>evill Spirits,</hi> or by good <hi>Angels,</hi> or by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of <hi>God</hi> by his <hi>holy Spirit</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this will lead us in the ſecond place to the conſideration of the ſeveral kinds of Dreams, diſtinguiſhed by the ſeveral <hi>cauſes</hi> thereof:</p>
               <p>Which are thus diſtinguiſhed, and that very well I think,<note place="margin">Leſſ. de juſtitiâ, l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>45.</hi> dub. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> by <hi>Leſſius</hi> in the Book before cited, <hi>de Juſtitiae.</hi> Some, ſaith he, proceed from the <hi>ſingular providence of God,</hi> to which thoſe may be reduced that are by the operation of <hi>good Angels.</hi> Some from the procuration of the <hi>Devil</hi> or <hi>evill Spirits.</hi> Some from the conſtitution of the <hi>Heavens,</hi> or diſpoſition of the <hi>Air.</hi> Some from <hi>previous cogitations,</hi> in which I ſhall include thoſe that proceed from the Affections or inclinations of the <hi>Mind:</hi> And ſome from the <hi>affection</hi> (as he calls it) or (as I had rather ſay) from the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106523:30"/>temper and complexion of the <hi>Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe that proceed from <hi>God</hi> either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, or by the miniſtration of his good <hi>Angels,</hi> are good, and true, and move to good, and are ſent unto <hi>good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,</hi> and though theſe were more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and eminent in thoſe times that went before the perfecting of the <hi>Canon of Scripture,</hi> as were alſo <hi>Apparitions,</hi> and extraordinary <hi>Inſpirations,</hi> yet there is no cauſe to doubt but that there may be, and are ſometimes (as extraordinary <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſpirations.</hi>) So <hi>divine Dreams,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>God</hi> is pleaſed to impart himſelf either <hi>immediately,</hi> or by the <hi>miniſtration</hi> of his <hi>Angels</hi> unto his people, either to diſcover ſome ſecret or future things unto them, or to encourage or give approbation unto ſome good things which they have in hand or deſign, or that he would ſet them upon, or to admoniſh them to avoid ſome things that would be hurtful unto them, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing unto him; and theſe Dreams muſt needs be of great concernment and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration;<note place="margin">Leſſius de juſtitiâ l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>43.</hi> dub. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Deus</hi> (ſaith Leſſius) <hi>illa nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam immittit niſi ad aliquid ſignifican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quo hominem moneat vel inſtruat.</hi> And as they are of great concernment and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, ſo it is a point of great wiſdom to know them.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:106523:30"/>
               <p>The Marks or Characters whereby they may be diſcerned, are obſerved, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveable to be theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When they bring with them either ſome certain declaration of words, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God declareth his will, or that which he would reveal or admoniſh a man of, or ſome certain repreſentation which hath ſome likeneſs or analogy unto the things whereof the mind is to be informed, or whereunto it is to be diſpoſed thereby, which if it do clearly and perſpicuouſly preſent that which the Dream intends, it is called, ſaith <hi>Leſſius,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>or a Viſion;</hi> if obſcurely and enigmatically, it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Dream. So that from hence we may collect indeed three ſorts of Divine Dreams,</p>
               <p>Firſt, By <hi>word or clear declaration,</hi> as was that of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> wherein he was admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed not to forſake the holy Virgin,<note place="margin">Mat. 1.20 Matth. 2.13, 19.</note> and was warned to fly into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and to return from thence.</p>
               <p>Secondly, By <hi>clear preſentation</hi> of the object, or by <hi>Viſion,</hi> as was that of <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 16 9.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, By way of <hi>Typical</hi> or <hi>Enig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical repreſentation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 37. Gen. 40. Gen. 41. Dan. 2.</note> as were the Dreams of <hi>Ioſeph, Gen.</hi> 37. of the Butler and Baker of <hi>Pharoah, Gen.</hi> 40. of <hi>Pharaoh, Gen.</hi> 41. of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, Dan.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:106523:31"/>
               <p>Indeed ſome may ſeem to be compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of two,<note place="margin">Gen. 31.10.</note> or of all theſe, as the Dream of <hi>Jacoh Gen.</hi> 31.10.</p>
               <p>And yet this Mark of it ſelf is ſomething too wide to diſtinguiſh this ſort of Dreams from others of the worſer ſort. For there is none of theſe ways but Satan and evil Angels may by Divine Permiſſion make uſe of; but this will ſhut out <hi>confuſed head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, extravagant Dreams</hi> from being of this ſort.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond Mark therefore is this, when they move unto that which is <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>eminently good,</hi> or from the <hi>contrary evill,</hi> and have nothing in them that ſtands op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Truth or <hi>Holineſs</hi> of the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>ſound Reaſon,</hi> nor that addeth any thing to <hi>Gods Word,</hi> as a new way of <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> or <hi>ſalvation;</hi> nor <hi>inclineth to exceed the limits or bounds of a mans Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or Vocation</hi> (unleſs in ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary caſe) and warranted by ſome extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary evidence. I accumulate all theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for brevity ſake.<note place="margin">Act. 16.9</note> See how S. <hi>Paul</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered his Dream to be from God, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When they are of a <hi>wiſe, ſober, of a juſt, and orderly frame and compoſure, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any tincture of lightneſs, gingling or vanity in them, or in the analogy that they have unto the things which they ſeem to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate or repreſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:106523:31"/>
               <p n="4">4. When they come unto thoſe that are <hi>good people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Gen. 20. Gen. 31.24.</note> or unto others in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of them, as they did unto <hi>Balaam</hi> on the behalf of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and unto <hi>Abimelech</hi> on the behalf of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and unto <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> on the behalf of <hi>Jacob;</hi> as alſo to <hi>Pharaoh, Nebuchadnezzar, &amp;c.</hi> Yet I do not ſay that this is <hi>proprium quarto modo,</hi> But it is that, that when it is preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs to the probability of the Dreams coming from God, although the contrary is not concluded by the abſence of this Mark; for we cannot ſay, but that God that <hi>ſendeth his rain upon the juſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt,</hi> may alſo give admonitions by Dreams tending to the temporal good of thoſe that are not <hi>gracious,</hi> or unto the ſpiritual good of thoſe that are yet <hi>wicked,</hi> that they may be made gracious by embracing them, or left inexcuſable in rejecting them, or for ſome other ends that are ſecret, and known onely unto God, at leaſt not unto us; or bringing unto ſuch wicked men the menaces of judgement and deſtruction, as the Dream of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Baker, and <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. When they come unto us being in an <hi>holy temper and diſpoſition of spirit,</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>intemperance,</hi> or any other ſinful <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper of mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:106523:32"/>
               <p n="6">6 When they come in ſome great <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> or <hi>ſtrait,</hi> or in ſome <hi>extraordinary caſe,</hi> or to admoniſh of ſome <hi>weighty mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> tending to ſome end that is clearly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and good; for God doth not uſe <hi>ſtrenue nihil agere,</hi> nor to uſe <hi>extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry means,</hi> but to ſome great and <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary purpoſe,</hi> or elſe in ſome <hi>great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. When it leaves, as an holy and humble, ſo a <hi>great</hi> and <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>certain impreſſion</hi> upon the <hi>Mind,</hi> moving it not upon car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal but <hi>ſpiritual Principles</hi> and <hi>motives,</hi> for the Spirit may be known much by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments he uſeth.</p>
               <p n="8">8. When the Deſign hath nothing in it <hi>unmerciful</hi> or <hi>uncharitable,</hi> nothing <hi>violent</hi> or <hi>raſh,</hi> not tending unto <hi>ſelf ends,</hi> or the ſatisfaction of a worldly or carnal mind</p>
               <p n="9">9. By the effect and conſequent of it in the ſoul as <hi>Leſſius</hi> hath it, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſi inde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maneat illuſtratio animi, conſolatio ſive promptitudo ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bſequium Dei;</hi> If there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main after, an holy clearneſs and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in the Spirit, an encreaſe of vigor and readineſs to godly obedience and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. <hi>A ſpiritual effect is a ſign that the Spirit was at work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. It may be known (ſaith <hi>Leſſius</hi>) by a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106523:32"/>
                  <hi>certain inward taſte and reliſh in the Soul;</hi> which I conceive is not to be expreſſed, nor can be underſtood by thoſe that have it not, nor can well be deſcribed by thoſe that have it. But this Mark, becauſe it is hard to be diſcerned, and may be counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited by him that knows how to appear in the form of an Angel of light, is to be attended unto with great <hi>humility, ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, prudence</hi> and <hi>caution,</hi> and is to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the compliance that it hath with the former Marks. Eſpecially we muſt ſee that that taſte and reliſh do not <hi>encourage</hi> us to any thing that is <hi>evil</hi> or <hi>ſinful,</hi> or diſcharge us from <hi>duty,</hi> or carry us on in worldly or <hi>carnal deſigns,</hi> or things that are frivolous and vain; but where it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with the reſt, it may have the force of a ſtrong <hi>aſſurance. Aliter enim</hi> (ſaith the Author before-named) <hi>afficiunt mentem ſomnia divinitus immiſſa, aliter aliunde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venientia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. When all the reſt being agreeable, it agreeth with ſome <hi>work</hi> that God hath <hi>in hand,</hi> and hath ſomething in it that ſeems to be <hi>above humane invention,</hi> and hath an excellent agreement in the ſeveral parts thereof, preſenting the ſame, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral things; is compoſed in a wiſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and order, and is approved by the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106523:33"/>event and exact conſequence of things.</p>
               <p n="12">12. And laſtly, When it comes <hi>unſought,</hi> and <hi>unexpected,</hi> nor hath any foundation in the <hi>fancies</hi> or <hi>apprehenſions of him that dreameth it, but preſenting things above his knowledge, or above his ordinary or uſual affections.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Filliucus Quaeſt. Moral. Tract.</hi> 24. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>n</hi> 123, 124. divides the Marks of Divine Dreams into two ſorts, 1. <hi>Thoſe that may deceive.</hi> 2. <hi>Thoſe that are more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the firſt ſort are theſe. 1. The truth of them in the ſucceſs; for the Devil may ſpeak truth in ſome things, that he may deceive in a greater matter 2. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitableneſs of the matter of them. 3. That they are of good acts, and ſeem to induce thereunto; for he doth ſometimes tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf into an Angel of light. 4. That they ſignifie future contingencies, or internal thoughts or myſteries of Faith; for all theſe things the Devil may diſcover by conjectures, out of the affections of men, and out of the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Of the ſecond ſort are theſe. 1. If no filthy or diſhoneſt thing happen in the Dream. 2. If it be probable that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not from natural cauſes. 3. If it leave the mind well diſpoſed to devotion.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106523:33"/>3. If the matter of the Dream induceth not to evill, or to vanity, or curioſity, but to good. 4. If the mind after the Dream be more apt and prompt unto good works. 5 If it render the mind certain that it is from God. In caſe of doubt he holds it ſafe to beleeve it to be from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Thoſe that proceed from the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>evil Angels</hi> are always evill, at leaſt in the deſign and end of them, and are to be rejected.</p>
               <p>Of theſe <hi>Baldwinus</hi> ſetteth down theſe ſeveral Marks,<note place="margin">Baldwin. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> de caſ. conſ. circa divinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem.</note> whereby he would have them concluded to be from the Devil, or evil ſpirits</p>
               <p n="1">1. When they tend to the <hi>inveſtigation or diſcovery of things ſecret or future, the knowledge whereof conferreth not to any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit (or true or ſolid good) but unto vain eſtentation of knowledge, or to the commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſome evil; then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we may well judge that ſuch Dreams are infuſed by the Devil; for the vanities of Science, and evil deſigns or contrivances are the works of the Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. When they tend to the <hi>leading of men from the holy Word of God to wicked doctrines or opinions, which are painted over with the pretence or colour of Revelations and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106523:34"/>divine Viſions,</hi> when they are indeed the <hi>meer deluſions of Satan transforming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into an Angel of light.</hi> Such, ſaith he, were the <hi>Dreams of the falſe Prophets</hi> of old, tending to Idolatry; and of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> who excuſed their Seditions and abſurd opinions and practiſes by <hi>Viſions</hi> and <hi>Dreams;</hi> and it were well that our <hi>Quakers</hi> and others that are carried away into ſtrange Fancies and irregular practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in this our Age and Nation would try their pretended <hi>inſpirations</hi> and <hi>Dreams by this rule,</hi> See <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. It is a ſign that Dreams are from the Devil and wicked ſpirits, when they are ſuch as <hi>inflame and ſtir up men unto luſt,</hi> to <hi>hatred or revenge,</hi> or the like evil affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whereby the <hi>Bodies</hi> alſo of thoſe that ſleep are <hi>defiled,</hi> and wherby they are indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to prayer, and the offices of piety to God, or charity to one another.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When Dreams come upon ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſeeking and expectation of them.<note place="margin">Leſſ. de juſtitiâ, l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>45.</hi> dub. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quando quis</hi> (ſaith Leſſius) <hi>divinationem per ſomnia quaerit certo modo vel ritu ſe componendo ad ſomnium: hoc enim expreſſe eſt invocare Diabolum.</hi> When any man doth purpoſely ſeek divination by Dreams, compoſing himſelf thereunto by ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Rites or Ceremonies; for this is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106523:34"/>to invocate the Devil.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dig. l. <hi>27.</hi> antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionum.</note> 
                  <hi>Thus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Heathens were wont with premiſed faſting, to ſleep in the skins of ſtain beaſts, that they might receive Anſwers or Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles in their ſleeps.</hi> According to that of <hi>Virgil.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Pellibus incubuit ſtratis ſomnoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> petebat.</l>
                  <l>He lay in skins beſpread upon the ground,</l>
                  <l>That he might anſwers have in ſleep profound.</l>
               </q>
               <p>As for thoſe Dreams which proceed from the diſpoſition of the <hi>Heavens</hi> and the <hi>Air,</hi> or from the buſineſſes or occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of the <hi>life,</hi> or from the humors, diſeaſes, or temper of the <hi>body,</hi> or from the affections, good or evil in their <hi>mind,</hi> they may be diſcerned probably by the <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpendencies</hi> that they have any of them <hi>reſpectively,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrat. de inſomni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is. Galen de praeſagio ex inſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niis.</note> unto any one or more of thoſe <hi>cauſes;</hi> eſpecially ſuch as proceed from the affections or diſpoſitions of the <hi>Body</hi> or <hi>Mind.</hi> 
                  <q>Thus (ſaith <hi>Leſſius</hi>) if a a man dream of fire, it is a ſign that he is troubled with choler; if of ſmoke, and darkneſs, of Funerals, or ſuch like ſad things, he is troubled with melancholy; if of rain, or ſnow, hail, or ice, with flegm;</q> If of mercy and chearful things,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106523:35"/>it ſeems to repreſent a ſanguine complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <q>If a man dreams that he flies, or runneth ſwiftly, it is obſerved to be a token of a light, healthy, and temperate complexion: If a man dream that he is laden with heavy burdens, or is in ſtrait places where he can hardly run or turn himſelf, it is a ſign that the animal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty is oppreſſed with humors.</q> 
                  <hi>Si ea quae ad libidinem pertinent, ſignum eſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundantiae ſpermatis. If a man dream that he is moiled with dirt, or dirty, it is a ſign that he aboundeth with putrid Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a ſtory of one that dreamt that he had his Thigh turned into a ſtone, who ſhortly after had that Thigh ſtricken with a Palſie. And when one had dreamt that he was in a Ciſtern full of blood, <hi>Galen</hi> conjectured that he was <hi>plethorical,</hi> or troubled with over-much <hi>abundance of blood.</hi> And thus that dream or trouble in ſleep, which the Phyſitians call <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the vulgar amongſt us, the <hi>Hag or Night-Mare,</hi> the Latines <hi>Incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> proceedeth (ſaith <hi>Leſſius</hi>) from a <hi>groſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len l. <hi>3.</hi> de lco. male affectis c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and obſcure, or fuliginous vapor ſeiſing upon the brain, and intercepting the courſes of the animal spirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such Dreams as theſe, are clearly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:106523:35"/>many times, at leaſt very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deriveable from their roots and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</p>
               <p>And yet it is not to be denied, but that there may ſome Dreames ſeemingly <hi>ſtrange</hi> and <hi>prophetical,</hi> proceed from ſome ſecret ſeeds, or indiſcernable appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of the <hi>approach of ſuch events</hi> which are in the Soul; the manner where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we cannot underſtand no more then we can underſtand the operations of the <hi>Loadſtone;</hi> the preſages that are found in <hi>Beaſts</hi> and <hi>Fowls,</hi> of the change of the <hi>Weather,</hi> or the ſence that the <hi>Cock</hi> hath of the ſeveral <hi>Watches</hi> of the night, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the day; or thoſe ſecret <hi>ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi> that are of <hi>cauſes</hi> towards their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects,<note place="margin">Opus na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae, opus intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiae, <hi>See</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaub. <hi>of Enthuſ.</hi>
                  </note> which may perhaps be felt and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by the ſtrange <hi>intelligence</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> when we our ſelves cannot tell how we come to the <hi>ſence</hi> or <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of them.</p>
               <p>Now if any ſhall be here deſirous to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, why ſuch kind of <hi>apprehenſions,</hi> as likewiſe thoſe <hi>impreſſions</hi> that are received from God or good Angels, or evil Spirits, ſhould be more incident to men in their <hi>ſleeps</hi> then when they are <hi>waking:</hi> Though it may be hard to give ſo clear an anſwer unto this doubt, as ſome would require;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106523:36"/>yet this may be ſomething towards a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of ſatisfaction, that one reaſon may be becauſe the ſoul is then uſually fitted thereunto by a twofold advantage. Firſt, By the advantage of the <hi>night,</hi> whereby it is delivered from thoſe <hi>noiſes</hi> and <hi>lights,</hi> and other <hi>objects</hi> which are apt to diſtract the <hi>notions,</hi> and hinder the <hi>intentions</hi> of the <hi>mind;</hi> which may be the reaſon (as I think it is) that there is no time ſo fit for <hi>ſtudy</hi> and <hi>meditation</hi> as the <hi>ſilent night.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then ſecondly, Becauſe of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of <hi>ſleep,</hi> whereby the ſoul is in a great part delivered from <hi>bodily operations,</hi> and from the buſineſs of the <hi>outward Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and from the commerce with external and worldly matters, which puts it as it were into a kind of <hi>Sabbath</hi> or <hi>ſtate of reſt;</hi> yea, in ſome ſort into a <hi>ſtate of ſeparation,</hi> though not from the bond of <hi>bodily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> yet from the trouble of <hi>Bodily o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration</hi> in ſome meaſure: Now the more <hi>quiet</hi> the ſoul is, and the more ſequeſtred from <hi>earthly</hi> and <hi>outward things,</hi> the more apt it is to enjoy the benefit of <hi>internal light,</hi> and of diſcourſe and intelligence from it ſelf, and the better fitted for <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual commerce</hi> either with <hi>God</hi> himſelf, or with <hi>ſpiritual Natures.</hi> Which may alſo lead us to underſtand ſomething to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106523:36"/>a reaſon why men drawing near their departure,<note place="margin">See <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaub.</hi> of Enthuſ.</note> when the Soul is drawing into a ſeparate condition by death, are obſerve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be diſpoſed to <hi>preſage</hi> and <hi>propheſie,</hi> and why people that are deprived of their Sences ſeem ſometimes to fall into fits of <hi>prophecying.</hi> See for our preſent purpoſe what the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Job</hi> 33.15,<note place="margin">Job 33.15, 16, 17</note> 16.17.</p>
               <p>To this alſo may be added, That in the time of ſleep, through the <hi>Antiperiſtaſis</hi> of the cold temper of the night, and by reaſon of the ſhutting up of the doors and <hi>pores of the Body,</hi> the Spirits are like a <hi>fire</hi> in a <hi>cloſe Furnace,</hi> more hot and active at leaſt to ſome purpoſes, and ſo more ſerviceable it may be to <hi>internal</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual operations</hi> and <hi>receptions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is time to come to ſome Rules, and ſo to draw towards a concluſion of this matter.</p>
               <p>That therefore we may know how to carry our ſelves in this matter as much as may be without offence to God, or hurt to our Souls;</p>
               <p>Firſt, Let this be laid down as the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,</hi> That as many Dreams are to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, and ſome to be rejected, <hi>abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> and <hi>repented of:</hi> ſo ſome are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and regarded, and may be attended
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106523:37"/>to unto good advantage and benefit. <hi>Nam vel omnibus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baldw. de caſ. conſ. circa di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>vel nullis fidem adhibere ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niis ejuſdem eſt vanitatis,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win.</hi>)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Divine Dreams</hi> that come unto us with good teſtimony that they are ſuch (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Rules before ſet down) are to be exceedingly regarded, as coming to us by Gods ſpecial, and ſometimes extraordinary <hi>work of Providence,</hi> which muſt needs be directed unto ſome weighty and good end,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Filliucius Quaeſt. Moral. Tract. 24. c. 5. n. 121.</hi> Sanctum &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarium eſſe fidem adhibere divinis ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niis patet, quia quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Deus loquatur, fides ei adhibenda eſt.</note> as we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, if we either conſider the firſt <hi>Mover,</hi> which is <hi>God;</hi> or the <hi>Instruments,</hi> which are his <hi>holy Angels.</hi> Such Dreams will challenge our very ſerious conſideration, and diligent care to take notice of thoſe admonitions, encouragements, or what elſe they offer unto us; and the neglect or contempt thereof cannot be committed without great impiety; and therefore we have not onely a warrant, but an unavoidable and inviolable <hi>obligation</hi> in point of <hi>duty,</hi> both in Obedience and Thankfulneſs, and in point of intereſt too, in order to the good of our ſelves or others, to take notice of ſuch Dreams, and to make uſe of them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their importance and purpoſe.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106523:37"/>Indeed we muſt firſt be careful to examine them and try them according to the Rules;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Filliuc. ib.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t his ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis fides adhibeatur, duo neceſſaria ſunt; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ut ſufficienter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtet Deum vel ejus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelum eſſe Auctorem ejus. Secundum, ut ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificatio ſomni aperta ſit.</note> and then when we have found them to be ſuch, we may and muſt regard and make the beſt, and the fulleſt, and the holieſt uſe of them we can.</p>
               <p>Secondly, We muſt by no means <hi>affect divination by Dreams,</hi> or put our ſelves thereupon having neither warrantahle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, nor any precept or allowance in the Word of God, no nor in ſound Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to encourage us thereunto; for this as it is a <hi>tempting of God,</hi> ſo it is alſo a grand practice of ſuperſtition, and as learned Mr. <hi>Caſaubon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſaub.</hi> of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſ.</note> is little differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent from <hi>Witchcraft.</hi> And this is amongſt thoſe things which are forbidden by God, <hi>Deut</hi> 18.10.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Filliuc. ib.</hi> Non licet futurorum, ſeu occul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum cognitionem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderare per ſomnia, niſi urgens neceſſitas &amp; ratio occurrat, vel niſi id fiat ex inſtinctie Sp. S.</note> See <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.26, 27. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and 29.8 Where the people are forbidden to <hi>hearken to their dreams which they cauſe to be dreamed,</hi> which doth very properly prohibit the affectation of Dreams; and all reliance upon ſuch as are ſought after: Indeed this is a ready way to ruine our ſelves, and to expoſe our ſelves to deluſions and deceits. <hi>If men</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:106523:38"/>(ſaith <hi>Caſaubon</hi>) <hi>give their minds to ſuch things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſaub.</hi> of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſm <hi>ch.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>there is no queſtion that they ſhall fancy ſometimes, nay often much more then there is juſt ground for.</hi> And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it may be ſomewhat may happen extraordinary;<note place="margin">Leſſius de justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ, l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>45.</hi> dub. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>but men, I think</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>were better want it by far, if it come by ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition,</hi> and not by immediate Providence, as (out of doubt) unto ſome ſometimes that are not ſuperſtitious. <hi>Leſſius</hi> hath a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation out of <hi>Gregory</hi> of a certain man that was given much to attend unto Dreams,<note place="margin">Greg. l. <hi>4.</hi> dial c. <hi>49</hi>
                  </note> that he was promiſed in his Dream <hi>that he ſhould live a long time,</hi> and when he had laid up great riches for the ſupply of that long life, which he thought himſelf aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of, <hi>He died ſuddenly.</hi> It is therefore well determined by learned Dr. <hi>Sanderſon</hi> in his Sermon upon <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. verſ. 6 <q>That ſince Scripture Canon ſealed,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon</hi>'s Sermon Gen. 20.6.</note> and the preaching of the Goſpel become Oecume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial, Dreams and other ſupernatural revelations as alſo other things of like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as miracles, and whatſoever more immediate and extraordinary manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the will and power of God have ceaſed to be ordinary and familiar; ſo as now we ought rather to ſuſpect delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in them, then to expect direction from them.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:106523:38"/>
               <p>Thirdly, Yet becauſe though God hath now tied us unto the ordinary means and <hi>directions of his Word and ſound Reaſon;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon</hi> ibid.</note> 
                  <q>beyond which we may not expect and againſt which we may not admit of any other direction (ſaith the learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor laſt named) as from God, yet he hath nowhere abridged himſelf of the power and liberty, even ſtill to inſinuate unto the ſons of men the knowledge of his will, and the glory of his might,<note place="margin">Joel 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.</note> by dreams and miracles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> (and let me add) ſince there is ſome promiſe of this unto his Church; if at any time, either in the want of ordinary means, or for the preſent neceſſity of the Church or of ſome part thereof, or for ſome other juſt cauſe perhaps unknown to us, he ſhall ſee it-expedient, as theſe kindes of extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manifeſtations are not to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected: ſo neither when they come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out affectation, and bring good and ſound appearance of righteous, and prudent and holy importance with them, and are upon trial approved to be from <hi>God,</hi> are they by any means to be neglected.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ubi ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>But we muſt take heed we give not too eaſie credit unto them, untill upon due trial they ſhall appear</hi> both in the end whereunto they point, a direct tendency to <hi>Gods glory,</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:106523:39"/>and in the means which they propoſe <hi>a conformity to Gods revealed will in his writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Take another Rule from the laſt named Author: <q>That ſo to obſerve our ordinary dreams, as thereby to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel future events, or fore-caſt therefrom good or ill luck in the ſucceſs of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, is a ſilly, groundleſs, unwarranted, and therefore unlawful, and a damnable ſuperſtition.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, As he goes on, <q>That there is yet to be made a lawful and very profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble uſe even of our ordinary Dreams, and of the obſerving thereof both in Phyſick and Divinity; not at all by foretelling things to come, but by taking from them ſome reaſonable conjecture of the ſtate of our bodies, becauſe the predominancy of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and differences of ſtrength and health, and diſeaſes, and diſtempers, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Diet or Paſſion, do cauſe differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent impreſſions upon the Fancy; our ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Dreams may be a good help to lead us into diſcoveries both of our natural conſtitution in time of health and of our diſeaſes in time of ſickneſs. And becauſe our Dreams look for the moſt part the ſame way which our ſecret thoughts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline us; they may be uſeful to finde out
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:106523:39"/>our ſins, and (as he obſerveth) our maſter ſin.</q> And to this is agreeable that of <hi>Leſſius; Si ſomnia putantur eſſe ex cauſâ naturali,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leſſius de juſtitiâ l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>45.</hi> dub. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>licitum eſt ex illis conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram facere de eventis quae ex illâ cauſâ prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venire ſelent;</hi> if Dreams appear to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed of a natural cauſe, it is lawful to make conjectures from them of thoſe events,<note place="margin">Leſſius ubi ſupra</note> which are wont to come from ſuch a cauſe.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Take this from the ſame <hi>Leſſius, When Dreams proceed from previous cares and cogitations, they ſignifie nothing of things to come, but do onely ſignifie that cauſe from which they proceed.</hi> Yet ſo they may be uſeful to us (I may ſay) to acquaint us the better with our ſelves, and to admoniſh us of our ſinful and diſtruſtful cares, for our good and reformation.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Let this be obſerved as a Rule of great concernment; That whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may be preſented unto us by <hi>Dreams</hi> or <hi>Enthuſiaſms,</hi> or any other way, nay, though by an aſſured viſion (if it were poſſible) of an innumerable company of heavenly Angels, or with the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of many and great miraculous operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that ſtandeth oppoſite to the <hi>dictates</hi> and <hi>revelations,</hi> and <hi>rules of God,</hi> and his <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or intendeth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:106523:40"/>to add any thing thereunto, as a way or means to attain unto ſalvation, is to be utterly rejected and abhorred as an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed <hi>deluſion,</hi> as likewiſe whatſoever tends to the diſcharging of us from any <hi>duty,</hi> or to move us to any <hi>impiety, impurity,</hi> or to <hi>uncharitable</hi> or <hi>evill thoughts</hi> of others without ground, or to any kind of <hi>wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> whatſoever; or to any thing that exceeds the <hi>bounds</hi> of our <hi>peculiar Callings,</hi> unleſs in ſome extraordinary caſe or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. See <hi>Deut.</hi> 13 1, 2.<note place="margin">Deut. 13.1, 2.</note> and that nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Scripture that all <hi>Quakers</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> may do well to ponder and ſtudy <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9.<note place="margin">Gal. 1.8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Though we,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, or an Angel from heaven preach any other Goſpel unto you,</hi> or (as it is in the original) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Preach any other thing unto you, beſides what ye have received,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Let him be accurſed,</hi> which is repeated again at verſ 9. with ſuch an earneſt <hi>reduplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as I think will hardly be found again in all the Book of God; or at leaſt very rarely; which ſhould admoniſh all to take the more notice of it, it being a Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture of that weight and force, that is able (if rightly underſtood and embraced) to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-throw all pretence of <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, whsch the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> boaſteth of,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106523:40"/>and of <hi>Angelical authority,</hi> or <hi>divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,</hi> which is the deluſion of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſts</hi> of our days, to inforce us to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any thing that is contrary to that ſaving Truth of the <hi>Geſpel,</hi> which is regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the Scripture, and was of old em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced by the people of God, or that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth any other way unto ſalvation, then that which is to be found therein.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, (which will follow upon the former) All Dreams, and ſo likewiſe all pretended Enthuſiaſms, Inſpirations, and Illuminations whatſoever, are to be <hi>tried</hi> and <hi>judged approved,</hi> or <hi>controuled</hi> by the <hi>revealed will of Almighty God in his holy Word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 8.19.</note> as alſo by the <hi>rule of ſound Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Prudence;</hi> and if they bring not a teſtimonial of conformity thereunto, they are by no means to be received. See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.19.</p>
               <p>And here by the way, give me leave to take notice of a very <hi>evil</hi> and <hi>unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able courſe</hi> that hath been taken up (if I be not miſtaken) by too many in theſe days, and hath received too much coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance from thoſe that are very highly obliged to the contrary; ſo that it hath been made the <hi>colour</hi> of <hi>great miſcarriages,</hi> whilſt <hi>ſome have taken upon them to ſeek un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God by faſting and prayer for his directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106523:41"/>and counſel in weighty affairs and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and neglecting to conſider or embrace what advice God hath laid down for their caſe and purpoſe in his Law, they have ſought and expected a return or anſwer by extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary motions and ſuggeſtions or inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which may ſort better with their (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) evill intereſts and deſigns.</hi> And ſo whilſt they have carried the <hi>Idol</hi> or <hi>ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling block</hi> of an <hi>evil intereſt</hi> in their heart, and in juſt judgment from <hi>God,</hi> are left to receive an anſwer agreeable thereunto, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from their own <hi>erring ſpirit,</hi> or the <hi>deluſion of Satan,</hi> they have taken his <hi>evill ſuggeſtions,</hi> or thoſe that have proceeded from their own <hi>corruptions</hi> (or at leaſt have ſeemed to take them) for the <hi>holy counſel of the Almighty.</hi> I am perſwaded it would be little leſs, if at all leſs pleaſing to God for them to go to an <hi>Heathen O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle,</hi> then to go to enquire of God upon ſuch terms. I wiſh that the ſerious read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and meditation of the eleven firſt verſes of <hi>Ezek</hi> 14.<note place="margin">Eze. 14.1. to 11.</note> might be rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and made good uſe of for the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of this and ſuch-like great <hi>miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ninethly, As all wicked Dreams are to be abominated, and ſome to be earneſtly repented of, which flow from our own
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106523:41"/>corrupt inclinations and affections. So vain, and fooliſh, impertinent, confuſed Dreams (ſuch as Dr. <hi>Jackson</hi> ſaith ariſe from the <hi>Garboiles of the fantaſie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Jackson</hi> in his ΜΑΡΑΝΑΘΑ or Commentaries upon Chriſts ſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion at the right hand of God, <hi>&amp;c. Sect.</hi> 3. <hi>ch.</hi> 9. <hi>ſect.</hi> 11 Eccleſ. 34.1, 2, 3.</note> and of which he thinks that of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> 34.1, 2, 3. is moſt true) are to be ſleghted, and thoſe that move unto <hi>ſuperſtitious fears,</hi> that would diſcourage from truſt in God, or from our chearful walking with him in duties.</p>
               <p>But yet laſtly, Thoſe <hi>Dreams</hi> that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>affectation</hi> offer themſelves unto us in a <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>calm temper,</hi> and are of a wiſe and orderly, of a <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>pure,</hi> of an <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>religious frame</hi> and <hi>method,</hi> not contradictory, but conſonant to the <hi>holy word of God,</hi> and <hi>ſound Reaſon,</hi> and tend to nothing but that which is juſt and holy, within the <hi>bounds of our Vocation,</hi> and to the <hi>glory of God.</hi> eſpecially when they come ſo clothed with <hi>opportunity</hi> and <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> as that they conduce to the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement or promotion of any good work that belongeth unto us, or that God hath undertaken, or is doing upon us, or by us upon others; or of any good and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſign in hand, or to the taking us off from any ſinful doubts, ſloth or impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:106523:42"/>that lie oppoſite thereunto, and lie open to any ſuch <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>prudent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etation,</hi> as they may well be preſumed to come from God, eſpecially falling out in <hi>extraordinary matters,</hi> or <hi>for the ſetting forward of more then ordinary deſigns;</hi> ſo they are to be prudently regarded and weighed, ſo as to take <hi>encouragment</hi> and <hi>admonition</hi> from them, and ſometimes they may inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate unto us <hi>things that are to come.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> An Application of what hath been ſaid unto the Converts Dream, together with the Interpretation thereof.</head>
               <p>IF we now compare what hath been laſt ſpoken with the Dream we have in hand, we ſhall finde it to be of good and warrantable conſideration for our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, it being ſuch, as firſt came in the tranſaction of a rare and extraordinary matter or buſineſs; The converſion of a Turk being ſuch as hath been rarely ſeen (I mean, of one that hath been born and bred in that religion.)</p>
               <p>Secondly, It hath no ſtamp but of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:106523:42"/>purity, prudence, and holineſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It came not upon any ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious expectation, or preparation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, it excellently complieth with the holy Word, and ſound Reaſon.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, It exactly anſwereth, in all the parts thereof, unto that holy buſineſs that was then in hand, and had been in motion the very evening before, for the <hi>converſion</hi> of the ſoul of him that dreamed it to <hi>God,</hi> and for his admiſſion to the Ordinances, Priviledges and graces of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, The interpretation thereof is <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>eaſie</hi> for the moſt part, yea, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indeed without any unreaſonable ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or croſſing of any one part of it againſt another; it is very full of <hi>harmony</hi> and <hi>concent,</hi> and yet <hi>above</hi> and <hi>beyond the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him that dreamed it,</hi> as the cafe was then.</p>
               <p>The Interpretation thereof is clear and eaſie for the moſt part.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Table with the Veſſell upon it like a Baſon or Font,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Dream.</note> doth very well repreſent the two Sacraments of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Supper of the Lord</hi> the two great <hi>Pledges</hi> and <hi>Seals</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106523:43"/>
                  <hi>communion,</hi> the one of our <hi>admiſſion</hi> or <hi>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> the other of our <hi>confirmation</hi> or <hi>growth</hi> in the <hi>fellowſhip of Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> and in the Graces of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The two men ſtanding by;</hi> The two Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters that were eſpecially emploied in the work of his <hi>converſion,</hi> to bring him to the fruition of the bleſſing of theſe <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The filthy ſtinking puddle ſtream where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſtood;</hi> The impure profeſſion of the <hi>Religion of Mahomet,</hi> wherein he was as yet held, which he had a deſire to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in; but it could give no purgation, but rather pollution unto his ſoul.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The dead Hen cut about the head, and dead of that wound, lying in the filthy ſtream, which a woman came and took out of that puddle, and ſet it upon her feet, ſo that it ran away alive,</hi> we could not very well tell what to make of; but he himſelf, after he was baptized (which may, I conceive, without offence, be taken for a ſpecial work of the Spirit in him) he himſelf, I ſay, the evening after his Baptiſm (as near as I can remember the time) interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it thus, or to this purpoſe; <hi>Sure</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that dead Hen that lay in the filthy ſtream, was my Soul that lay dead in the puddle of my errors; The Woman was the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:106523:43"/>Church of God</hi> (which is preſented as a woman in the Scripture.) <hi>which hath taken my dead Soul out of the puddle of my errors, and reſtored me to life, even to the life of grace, which having recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he now runs from that filthy ſtream of the Mahometan deluſions.</hi> (Let me add this) That as that Hen lay dead of a wound in the head, ſo he was dead in the blindneſs and <hi>errors</hi> of his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> or <hi>Minde,</hi> which is, as it were, <hi>vulnus in capite,</hi> a wound in the head, that being held to be the ſeat of the knowing or judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Faculties or Powers.</p>
               <p>The full and fair ſtream that guſhed out ſuddenly, and brake in with great force upon that <hi>current</hi> of <hi>corruption,</hi> and drove it clean away, and preſentied it ſelf in the place of it, which he entred into at firſt with ſome timorouſneſs, and by degrees, and afterward waſhed himſelf in it, and ſwam over it;</p>
               <p>The holy water of <hi>Baptiſmal regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or the ſtream of the Truth and grace of the Goſpel, which hath ſuddenly through the goodneſs of the Lord, and very powerfully, broken in upon his Soul, and driven away the puddle of his <hi>former cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions;</hi> which he was fearful to enter into at the firſt, but hath now waſhed therein
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:106523:44"/>for the cleanſing of his ſoul, and will we hope ſwim through it unto the Haven of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal happineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The thirſt that was upon him after his waſhing;</hi> The deſire which he expreſſed after the Lords Supper, or an holy long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after ſpiritual things, and the comforts of the Goſpel, or after happineſs; which Thirſt can finde nothing upon earth to quench it; the ſhowre from Heaven, the ſhowre or dews of heavenly bleſſing, or of divine illumination and grace, which he could not tell how to receive of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>The poor houſe that he knockt at,</hi> The habitation of the Church now in a poor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted condition, deſtitute of earthly mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence and glory. <hi>The woman that came forth,</hi> That afflicted Church. <hi>The diſh ſhe gave him.</hi> The Ordinances and means of grace, whereby the heavenly dews we hope will be more and more conveyed into his ſoul, to the quenching of all evil thirſts after tranſitory things, and to the eternal refreſhing of his Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:106523:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of ſome further progreſs made in the converſion of Mr. <hi>Dandule,</hi> and of another remarkable paſſage of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence that fell out for the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and encouragement thereof.</head>
               <p>THis ſtrange dream having made ſome impreſſion upon the heart of this Convert, as we may reaſonably beleeve, whereby the bars of his ſoul were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhaken and looſened, for the ſetting open of the gates for the admiſſion of that Goſpel light wherewith God hath been pleaſed now to illuſtrate his ſoul; we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed our attempts with ſome earneſtneſs and diligence that morning, and prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at length ſo far by the divine aſſiſtance, as to obtain of him, <hi>to joyn with us in prayer for the aſſiſtance and direction of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God in the carrying on of the work of his converſion;</hi> and afterwards he was with us in the performance of the <hi>ſervice of the Church</hi> for that <hi>morning,</hi> at my houſe, and kneeled down &amp; joyned with us when we uſed the <hi>Lords Prayer;</hi> in this we made uſe of the help of his <hi>Interpreter,</hi> that he might repeat it after us.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:106523:45"/>
               <p>And in this holy buſineſs I cannot think fit to omit one remarkable paſſage of the divine Providence which fell out in the performance of divine Worſhip at that time, whereby the Lord may ſeem to have ſeconded that of his Dream and it was this.</p>
               <p>It pleaſed God (which we neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned nor foreſaw) ſo to order the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in that holy plot that he had laid for the bringing home of this ſoul into his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, and for the reducing of this <hi>loſt ſheep</hi> into his <hi>fold;</hi> of this <hi>loſt peice</hi> of ſilver in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <hi>treaſury;</hi> and of this <hi>Prodigal childe</hi> from his <hi>Mahometan empty husks</hi> unto his <hi>Fathers houſe, The holy Church of Chriſt;</hi> That in the ordinary courſe of the Church, the <hi>Second Leſſon</hi> which we read appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for that very morning in the <hi>diſpoſition</hi> of the <hi>Church Calender,</hi> fell out to be the Fifteenth Chapter of the Goſpel of S. <hi>Luke,</hi> where we have the parable of the <hi>poor loſt wandering ſheep</hi> brought home upon the <hi>ſhoulders</hi> of the <hi>good Shepheard</hi> unto his <hi>flock;</hi> of the <hi>ſilver piece</hi> that was <hi>loſt</hi> and <hi>found again;</hi> and of the <hi>Prodigal childe returned unto his Fathers houſe and Boſom,</hi> and there entertained with great love, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody and rejoycing: where alſo at the ſeventh verſe I found my Text, upon which God directed me to preach at the time of his Baptiſm.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:106523:45"/>
               <p>When in the reading of that Chapter, I obſerved that <hi>gracious Providence,</hi> I could not paſs it by without ſome notes upon it, and therefore by his Interpreter I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated unto him, that he might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in have a taſte of <hi>Gods care of his ſoul, that was pleaſed ſo wiſely and carefully to order things that we thought not off, for the ſpeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and promoting of the work of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Withal, I offered him ſome obſervations upon the Chapter, tending to the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the <hi>wretched condition</hi> of one that was <hi>ſtraied</hi> and loſt from <hi>God</hi> in the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings and <hi>wilderneſs of ſin</hi> and <hi>error,</hi> and of the wonderful and tender mercy of the Lord in ſeeking after, and receiving into his boſom ſuch <hi>poor ſinners</hi> returning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; and of the great <hi>treaſures</hi> of his goodneſs and <hi>Bowels of his mercy,</hi> that he is ready to open and pour out unto them. And by way of Application, I ſhewed him, that he was in the ſeveral parts of that Chapter; he was the <hi>loſt ſheep</hi> that Chriſt was even now <hi>ſeeking</hi> in the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors of his <hi>Miniſters</hi> for his <hi>Converſion,</hi> that he might bear him upon the <hi>ſhoulders</hi> of his <hi>heavenly ſtrength</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> unto the <hi>Fold</hi> of his <hi>Church:</hi> He was the <hi>loſt peece</hi> that had been trodden under the feet
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:106523:46"/>of the <hi>spiritual adverſaries,</hi> and defaced by the filth and pollution of <hi>error</hi> and ſin, which the Lord was now about to recover into his treaſury.</p>
               <p>He was that <hi>wandering</hi> and <hi>wretched Prodigal</hi> that had been feeding upon the <hi>husks</hi> of <hi>error</hi> and <hi>vanity,</hi> and that was brought unto great <hi>miſery,</hi> whom the tender Father, though he ſaw him afar off at the great diſtance of the <hi>errors</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections</hi> that were in him, yet would <hi>run</hi> to meet, if he would but <hi>turn</hi> to him with <hi>ſincerity,</hi> and would entertain him with <hi>great love, mercy, and joy,</hi> would fall upon his neck and <hi>kiſs him with thckiſſes of divine love,</hi> would put the <hi>Ring</hi> upon his <hi>finger,</hi> would <hi>marry</hi> him unto himſelf, and give him the pledge of his <hi>everlaſting love,</hi> would put the <hi>beſt Robe</hi> upon him, even the <hi>Robe of the righteouſneſs of Chriſt</hi> for his <hi>juſtification,</hi> and of the <hi>ornaments</hi> of the holy and <hi>heavenly graces of his Spirit,</hi> for the ſanctification of his ſoul.</p>
               <p>Would kill the <hi>fatted Calf,</hi> would feaſt him with the mercies, graces, and comforts of the Goſpel in Chriſt Jeſus, who died for his ſalvation.</p>
               <p>Would refreſh him, and ſolace him with the heavenly <hi>muſick</hi> and <hi>harmony</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:106523:46"/>of <hi>Divine Peace,</hi> and his <hi>heavenly love,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And thus the Lord was pleaſed to faſten another chain of his <hi>Divine Providence</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Soul; and added unto that dream in his ſleep another teſtimony of that watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful care that he had over that buſineſs we had in hand for his good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> A Diſcourſe concerning this laſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and for the juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, by the propoſal of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers examples of Admonitions given and taken from Providenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al occurrences of the like ſort out of Scripture, and other Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</head>
               <p>BUt this obſervation will perhaps be accounted <hi>frivol us</hi> and <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> by ſome, and may be abuſed by others; and therefore I crave leave a little to ſay ſomething for the vindication of it from the firſt, and to give ſome <hi>cautions</hi> for the prevention of the ſecond.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:106523:47"/>
               <p>And firſt, That it may not be thought <hi>frivolous</hi> or <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> that we have taken notice of that <hi>Providential occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> I ſhall give you ſome warrant for the juſtification of our obſervation, both out of the Scripture and other approved Authors. Firſt, We finde the divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in a kinde not much unlike this, commended unto our conſideration in the holy Book of God; ſuch was that that fell out unto the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> when the like work of <hi>converſion</hi> was drawing near up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and that <hi>in order to the promoting of that like gracious deſign that God had upon him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 8.27, to 34.</note> Act 8.27. to 34. where it was ſo ordered by the divine <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> that that place of Scripture,<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53 7. was then in reading by the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> when St. <hi>Philip</hi> was ſent by the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> to draw near unto his <hi>Chariot,</hi> by the explication whereof from the mouth of St. <hi>Philip,</hi> he was converted to the <hi>Faith of Chriſt,</hi> and was <hi>baptized</hi> in the way as he went, God making uſe of that <hi>Providential occurrence</hi> to promote his <hi>commerſion</hi> to the <hi>Goſpel-truth;</hi> meeting him in his paſſage,<note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> as he met St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his <hi>journey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Fourth of <hi>Luke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 4.16, 17, 18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> we read that our bleſſed Savior being in the Synagogue
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106523:47"/>at <hi>Nazareth, there was delivered unto him the Book of the Prophet Iſaiah, and when he had opened the book, he found the place</hi> (it may not improbably imply that upon the opening of the Book he found that excellent place of Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1, 2,<note place="margin">Iſ. 61.1, 2</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wherein is contained our <hi>Saviors annoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>commiſſion</hi> for the ſulfilling of that <hi>great Office</hi> of the <hi>Savior</hi> of the <hi>World</hi>) offered it ſelf by <hi>Providence</hi> firſt unto his view, that it might give him the occaſion of that holy diſcourſe, that he made then unto the people, ſhewing how <hi>that very place was fulfilled in him that day before their eyes.</hi> Whether he looked for it, or fell upon it by providence, is uncertain (ſaith one of our late Commentators.) I confeſs it is not very certain, but yet the words do unto me ſeem moſt probably to imply ſo much, that he fell upon it by Providence; eſpecially in the Original, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the opening, or upon the opening of the Book he found the place where it was written. I am ſure enough we may ſafely think ſo: for as all things that ſeem moſt caſual even to the <hi>falling of a Sparrow,</hi> nay, of an <hi>hair from the head,</hi> are under the care and guidance of the <hi>divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 10.29, 30.</note> 
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.29, 30, ſo we may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:106523:48"/>our ſelves that that <hi>Divine Providence</hi> is eſpecally watchful for the ordering of all things (even the ſmalleſt matters) that can be thought of in the world to ſerve that <hi>great deſign</hi> of the bringing of <hi>Gods people to ſalvation</hi> by Chriſt Jeſus. That Greek ſentence is excellent, which Mr. <hi>Down</hi> hath, he telleth us not from whence, in his Treatiſe about Lots in gaming, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>They that speak of the laying of stones, tell us that the great ſtones cannot be well placed without the ſmaller. So</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>alſo in the Government of the world, for the better erdering of the greateſt things, God takes care of the ſmalleſt alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Something very obſervable of a nature near unto our caſe, we may find in the ſixth of <hi>Eſther, ver.</hi> 1. where we finde a <hi>multiplied Providence</hi> in the ordering of matters in eſteem <hi>caſual,</hi> for the diverſion of that cruel deſign that <hi>Haman</hi> had for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing of the death of <hi>Mordecai,</hi> when the Gallows was made for poor <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and the next morning, that great Favorite that thought he had the <hi>key</hi> and the <hi>ſtern</hi> too of the Kings heart in his mouth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſue out the Commiſſion for his execution, whoſe life was the blaſt of all his comforts: <hi>God</hi> orders the matter ſo by
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:106523:48"/>the miniſtry of <hi>an Angel</hi> (as one ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth) that <hi>the King could not ſleep</hi> that very night (for we may aſſure our ſelves no man can at any time ſleep, when God hath any thing to do with his waking for the good and benefit of his people; not the ſofteſt beds, not the darkeſt night, nor the wearieſt journeys or labors in the day, nor the plentifulleſt cups, nor the warmeſt cloaths, nor the quieteſt heart, nor the ſtrongeſt opium can prevent or diſappoint ſuch a purpoſe of the Almighty.) God kept <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> waking, becauſe he had ſome bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to do with him about <hi>Mordecai,</hi> to counterplot the deſign of <hi>Haman;</hi> and when he found that he could not ſleep, God finds him out an employment to paſs away the tediouſneſs of a waking night.</p>
               <p>It is the obſervation of <hi>Cornel. à Lapide</hi> out of <hi>Herodotus</hi> (as I remember) that it was <hi>a laudable cuſtom received among the Perſians, That thoſe good and meritorious performances, whereby any man had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved well of the King or Kingdom, ſhould be recorded in the publick Annals or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials, that they might not be forgotten in the reward:</hi> And this agrees well with our ſtory in <hi>Eſther,</hi> ſuch a record there was of that faithful ſervice that <hi>Mordecai</hi> did,<note place="margin">Eſth. 2.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſth.</hi> 2.21. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This lay aſleep for a time,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:106523:49"/>and was forgotten, but when the time of need cometh, then <hi>God</hi> revives it, who lays up <hi>mercies aforehand for his Children, and brings them out when opportunitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires;</hi> and this was <hi>a now or never;</hi> for after the next mornings work, if <hi>Haman</hi> had ſped, it had been too late. Therefore now in this very night, that he might be ſure to remember it in the morning, and that he might prevent the deſign and ſuit of <hi>Haman,</hi> the King being deprived of his reſt, muſt needs call for the <hi>Records of the Chronicles,</hi> little thinking what Gods purpoſe was, or what a <hi>Lecture</hi> God had to read to him in that <hi>Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when this Book is brought unto him, <hi>That muſt be the place by Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, that muſt then needs be read unto him,</hi> either in the courſe of the <hi>reading,</hi> or perhaps by <hi>chance,</hi> where poor <hi>Mordecat</hi>'s <hi>Neck-verſe</hi> was, where it was found writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that <hi>Mordecai</hi> had told of <hi>Bigthana</hi> and <hi>Tereſh, two of the Kings Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, the keepers of the door, who ſought to lay hand on the King</hi> Ahaſuerus: honeſt <hi>Moràecai</hi> would not be an acceſſary no not ſo much as by concealment unto Treaſon or Treachery againſt a Heathen King; and ſee how <hi>God bleſſeth Fidelity and allegiance;</hi> this faithful and honeſt act of his is in bank
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106523:49"/>for him againſt the time of his <hi>neceſſity,</hi> and is by this <hi>providential diſpoſition</hi> of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty</hi> in this <hi>nick of time</hi> preſented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of the King, to the turning of <hi>Hamans</hi> wicked deſign for <hi>Mordecai</hi>'s ſhame and death, to his ſafety and honor; and to <hi>return</hi> at length his intended <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief upon himſelf,</hi> whilſt <hi>Mordecai's</hi> eſcape gives the time for the procuring of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> condemnation, and for the defeat not onely of that bloody purpoſe which he had now for the ruine of <hi>Mordecai,</hi> but of that alſo which he had for the <hi>deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Jews;</hi> and all this great evill is prevented, and ſo great good, ſo joyful a deliverance brought to paſs, by the (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) <hi>caſual turning</hi> of the leaf of a Book, or by the <hi>order or courſe</hi> which then fell out in the <hi>Kings reading</hi> of the <hi>Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; Natura nuſquam magis quam in mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis,</hi> ſo ſaith one; and we may further ſay, I think, <hi>Providentia nuſquam magis quam in minimis;</hi> The Providence of God is very wonderful in turning the <hi>greateſt ſcales</hi> with the <hi>ſmalleſt grains;</hi> in making ſo ſmall, ſo inconſiderable a matter as the turning of a <hi>leaf in a Book</hi> at ſuch a time to be the means to prevent the <hi>ruine of a Nation.</hi> Oh learn to admire and obſerve the <hi>Providence of God</hi> in the <hi>ſmalleſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:</hi> An holy curioſity of this kind is both
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:106523:50"/>pious and profitable; who can conſider it and not adore him? And conſider withal, with how ſmall a matter God can deliver a Nation, even with the <hi>turning of a leaf,</hi> and what great uſe he can make of the <hi>orderly courſe of reading,</hi> who can think on it, and not fear him and truſt in him? He that did this with the turning of a leaf, can do as much with the turning of a ſtraw.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Conſider what great bleſſing the ſmalleſt matters in the world may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter unto us, if they be guided to our good by the gracious Providence of God; and what miſery and miſcheif may grow up out of the ſmalleſt ſeeds, the pooreſt and moſt inconſiderable occurrences, if God do not ſhine through them unto us, and do not order them for our benefit, or ſhall appoint them to be inſtrumental to our hurt or deſtruction.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, See here not onely the <hi>truth</hi> but the <hi>reaſon</hi> of <hi>Gods univerſal Providence</hi> in the ordering of the <hi>ſmalleſt things</hi> and motions of the world, ſince we ſee that he makes even the ſmalleſt matters ſervsceable to his great aad <hi>wonderful mercies</hi> and <hi>judgments.</hi> We cannot tell what God hath to do with a <hi>ſingle ſtraw</hi> that ſwimmeth down the <hi>water;</hi> And may not this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence make ſomething to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106523:50"/>of people not to be ſo much out of love as they have been with the orderly courſe of the Churches readings?</p>
               <p>We have diſcovered, I hope, ſo much countenance from theſe examples in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that may <hi>ſecure us from any juſt charge of ſuperſtition</hi> in that obſervation that we have made of that which fell out in the courſe of the reading by the courſe of the Church, in order to the converſion of this perſon.</p>
               <p>And having taken notice of this, I hope we may with the greater freedom and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence offer to conſideration ſome other paſſages of the like nature that have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen others in the records of the ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sulpitius Severus,</hi> in the life of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sulpit. Severus in vita Martini.</note> hath a relation to this purpoſe; that when the people of <hi>Turonica</hi> were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to chuſe that holy man to be Biſhop of that place, and one of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> that were then preſent, whoſe name was <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſor,</hi> amongſt others was a principal op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of his election: The Reader (whoſe office it was to read the Scriptures that day) being wanting, another that was preſent, taking up the Book of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> fell a reading at that place which preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſelf firſt unto his view, which was
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106523:51"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. at the ſecond or (as it is there cited) at the <hi>third verſe</hi> of which Pſalm the words in that Tranſlation which was then uſed,<note place="margin">Pſ. 8.2, 3</note> are thus rendered, <hi>Ex ore infantium &amp; lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium perfeciſti laudem, propter inimicos tuos ut deſtruas Defenſorem; Out of the mouth of Babes and Sucklings thou haſt perfected praiſe becauſe of the Enemies, and that thou mayſt deſtroy Defenſor,</hi> or <hi>the Defender;</hi> which having ſuch a reflexion on his name (as it was apprehended) the people took as a teſtimony from Heaven againſt him, and his attempt in oppoſing the election of their Biſhop, as if that Pſalm had been appointed by <hi>Divine Providence</hi> to be then read upon that occaſion, and ſo the people fell a ſhouting, and the contrary party was confounded.</p>
               <p>It may be this may ſeem a <hi>little too light,</hi> nor do I preſs it to be valued any more then the weight of it ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade.</p>
               <p>Theſe that follow will, I hope, be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to be conſiderable to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>As firſt,<note place="margin">Austin. Confeſſ. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> That which St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of <hi>Antonius,</hi> that whilſt he was yet hanging off as it were from God towards the world,<note place="margin">Mat. 19.21.</note> caſually lighting upon that place, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.21. <hi>Vade &amp; vonde om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:106523:51"/>&amp;c. Go and ſell all that thou haſt, and give to the poor, and thou ſhalt have treaſure in heaven, and come and follow me;</hi> he was thereupon preſently converted.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Auguſt. Confeſſ. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> that which he relateth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the ſame Twelfth Chapter of the Eighth Book of his <hi>Confeſſions</hi> (which it ſeems had ſomewhat the more impreſſion upon him, from the conſideration that he had of the former example.) The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was this; when he was in great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity of ſpirit in thoſe <hi>beginnings</hi> and <hi>preparations of the work</hi> of <hi>converſion that were upon him,</hi> he heard a voyce, as he thought, from the neighboring houſe, as of Boys or Girls ſinging in theſe words, <hi>Toile lege, Tolle lege; Take up and read, Take up and read;</hi> which he taking to be <hi>an admonition from Heaven,</hi> went ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the place where he had left his Book of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, and upon the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof found that place preſented it ſelf unto his view,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Non in comeſſationibus, &amp;c. Not in rioting and drunkenneſs, not in chambering and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs, not in ſtrife and envying, but put you on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make not proviſion for the fleſh to fulfill the luſts thereof;</hi> Whereby the clouds of thoſe doubtings and waverings that were upon
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106523:52"/>his ſoul were preſently ſcattered, and he brought into a chearful reſolution, to give up himſelf in holy Religion to God, to the joy of his pious Mother, and the comfort of his own ſoul.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Euſeb. Eutic. Hiſtor.</note> That of <hi>Origen,</hi> I conceive, is not to be omitted; He living in a time of <hi>temptation</hi> and <hi>perſecution,</hi> and having a great deſire to draw people from Idolatry, and being deluded, as it ſeems, with hopes that ſome would be baptized upon a day wherein they were to offer incenſe unto the falſe gods, was ſtirred up with <hi>zeal</hi> in his heart to do his endeavour to turn ſome people unto Chriſt; and to that end, he makes ſo much haſte unto the place where that Idolatry was to be committed;<note place="margin">Planctus <hi>Origen.</hi> Ego vero infaelix an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te diluculum de stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to exiliens nec orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem quidem conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam implere potui; ſed deſiderans omnes homines ſalvos fieri &amp; in cognitionem ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis venire, meip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum in Diaboli la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queis implicavi.</note> truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (it may be too much, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> did) <hi>upon his own ſtrength and reſolution therein, that he emitted his ordinary morning devotion</hi> (which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire may be obſerved) and coming to the place, and being left unto himſelf by God (whoſe ſervice he had neglected that morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and whoſe direction and aſſiſtance it may be he had not ſo carefully ſought as he ſhould have done) <hi>inſtead of diverting
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:106523:52"/>others from their Idolatrous practice, he was through weakneſs drawn into it himſelf,</hi> and ſo took a very dreadful and dangerous fal; chuſing rather to offer incenſe, then to have his Body defiled by a filthy Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, which it ſeemeth was threatened. After this being at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> whether he went being aſhamed to continue at <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> and there requeſted to preach or expound the Scriptures unto the people; when he was entering upon the buſineſs, and had opened his Book, there was firſt, it ſeems preſented unto his view that place of the <hi>Fiftieth</hi> or as it is otherwiſe reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>the Forty ninth Pſalm</hi> at the <hi>ſixteenth verſe, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Pſ. 50.16</note> But unto the wicked God ſaith, What haſt thou to do to declare my Statutes, or that thou ſhouldeſt take my Covenant in thy mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt inſtruction, and caſteſt my words behind thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereat he was ſo <hi>ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> and <hi>ſtartled,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Planctus ſeu lamentum <hi>Origenis</hi> inter opera ejus. Maceriam poſuit ori meo, coactus ſum à ſanctis Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopis in doctrinae verbum prorumpere; &amp; accepto co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice Pſalmorum orans ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rui, &amp; aſcendit mihi elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium illud quod confun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor dicere, eloqui compellor; Peccatori autem dixit Deus, Quare tu enarras juſtitias meas; &amp; aſſumis teſtamentum meum per os tuum?</note> as if <hi>God himſelf had flaſhed with heavenly lightning into his face in the reading of thoſe words, that his mouth was ſtopped,</hi> and inſtead of a <hi>flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of words,</hi> he brake forth
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:106523:53"/>into a <hi>flood of tears.</hi> And when he had made a paſſage for his language through that great <hi>ſtorm</hi> and dreadful <hi>tempeſt</hi> that was raiſed in his ſoul, inſtead of inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the people, he fell into a greivous <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation</hi> and <hi>deploration</hi> of himſelf and <hi>of his own horrid ſins, and his wretched con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:</hi> Which we have recorded in the works of <hi>Origen,</hi> with ſo much bitterneſs of ſpirit, and deep humiliation of ſoul, as his expreſſions repreſent, as I think can hardly finde a parallel in the Eccleſiaſtical Story; and therefore we cannot I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive without breach of charity, and without condemning our ſelves who come ſo far ſhort of it, doubt but it was accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God: And as little reaſon have we to make any queſtion but there was a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and wiſe, and holy work of Gods all-diſpoſing Providence in the matter.</p>
               <p>I might here ſet down ſome remarkable paſſages of this nature, that have fallen out in our unhappy days, at the time of a great <hi>trial and cataſtophe</hi> in this Nation, when the <hi>readings of the day did very aptly anſwer the ſad condition of a great perſon in this Realm.</hi> But it may be this would more provoke then edifie.</p>
               <p>It will be ſafer to tell you that it is related of <hi>Franciſcus Junius,</hi> that is joyned with
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106523:53"/>
                  <hi>Tremelius</hi> in the Tranſlation of the Old Teſtament,<note place="margin">See <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaub</hi> of Enthuſ. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>That he was not converted to be heartily a Chriſtian untill the firſt words of St.</hi> Johns <hi>Goſpel were offered unto him by a ſtrange Providence, as he conceived.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things I hope may ſerve for the juſtification of our fore-mentioned Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of Divine Providence, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent uſe thereof.</head>
               <p>BUt it will be requiſite I conceive, to ſay ſomething by way of caution, leaſt any ſhould abuſe it, or thoſe other things that have been produced of the like nature to the encouragement or countenance of ſuperſtition.</p>
               <p>There was indeed (as learned <hi>Pencerus</hi> writeth in his Book <hi>de Divinatione,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pencerus de divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione.</note> and his Treatiſe <hi>de Sortibus</hi>) <hi>A certain ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious kinde of Sortilegy or Lottery amongſt the Heathens, which were ſtiled</hi> Sortes Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilianae, <hi>Cum aperto libri codice qui primi viſu occurriſſent verſus in oraculi omen aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumebantur:</hi> When the Book being
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:106523:54"/>opened at adventure for the purpoſe, the firſt verſes or lines that were preſented to the eye, were taken to have the force of an oracle. An example whereof, as <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerus</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Helius.</note> is remembred by <hi>Helius Spartianus</hi> in the life of <hi>Adrian,</hi> which <hi>Adrian being on a time ſolicitous concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the mind of the Emperor towards him, and deſiring to be reſolved by this Virgilian Sortilegy, upon the opening of the Book met with theſe verſes,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Quis procul ille autem ramis inſignis olivae</l>
                     <l>Sacra ferens? noſco crines incana<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> menta</l>
                     <l>Romani regis, primus qui legibus urbem</l>
                     <l>Fundabit, curibus parvis, &amp; paupare terrâ,</l>
                     <l>Miſſus in imperium magnum.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now that this was, and that all ſuch practices are ſuperſtitious and impious, there is no queſtion to be made, as being no better then Witchcraft, and conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Devil; and that though the Book of the holy Scripture it ſelf ſhould be uſed in any ſuch way, as to put any thing or event upon ſuch a trial thereby, the holineſs of that Book would be ſo far from excuſing or diminiſhing the ſin that it were ſo much the greater, and more abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable iniquity; for <hi>the holier any thing
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:106523:54"/>is in the right uſe, the more wicked is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe thereof. Corruptio optimi peſſima.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That therefore whilſt we labor to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that which is good and lawful, we do not through unwarineſs encourage any unto that which is evil, which is too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten done:</p>
               <p>I ſhall endeavor to ſet down ſome ſafe and neceſſary Rules and Cautions to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in matters of this nature.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Concerning matters of Providence in general.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Concerning the uſe of Lots, which are re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ucible thereunto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Concerning the Obſervations that may be made of remarkable Providenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urrences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, This is a ſafe and certain Rule, <hi>That it is not onely lawful, but the duty of all people to take special notice of the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages and diſpenſations of the holy Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God;</hi> and that even in thoſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences thereof, which ſeem unto us through the ignorance of the dependance that is between <hi>cauſes and effects,</hi> to be very caſual and contingent, which is very clear not onely from thoſe many places of the <hi>holy Scripture</hi> which preſent the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidential works of God</hi> unto our conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and earneſtly call upon us for our
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:106523:55"/>meditation thereupon, and rebuke the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect; but alſo from ſound and clear reaſon, and the many excellent uſes that may and ought to be made thereof.</p>
               <p>The Providence of God is his <hi>great treaſury,</hi> abounding with excellent and precious riches from whence we may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich and furniſh our ſouls with many excellent documents and divine inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>It is a great and <hi>glorious Theatre</hi> wherein we may behold the great and magnificent and wonderful ſpectacles of the operations of the perfections and attributes of God, and ſee the divine Artificer at work in the great ſhop or laboratory of the world, and there making uſe of his ſeveral Agents and Inſtruments, of Angels and Men good and bad, of the heavenly Bodies, and of all the creatures in the variety of their motions and effects to thoſe various and wonderful purpoſes and products where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they are imployed by the divine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and that many times againſt their own purpoſes and deſigns.</p>
               <p>Here we may ſee him by the art and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of his divine wiſdom and holineſs, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing a ſtrange and wonderful Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry (as I may ſo ſpeak) making extracts of good out of every evill, light out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:106523:55"/>holineſs out of ſin, and the greateſt good out of the greateſt evill; as the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the world out of the treaſon of a <hi>Judas,</hi> and the malice and cruelty of the wicked Jews.</p>
               <p>Here we may ſee him in the <hi>Divine ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties</hi> and wiſe contrivances of his heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly policy, countermining the deſigns, and blaſting the counſels of the crafty <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phels,</hi> the greateſt and wiſeſt Politicians of the world, taking them in the nets that themſelves have woven, and making their turning of things upſide down,<note place="margin">Iſ. 29.16.</note> to be but like the turning or treading of the clay for the Potter, out of which, when they have done all they can, he frameth what veſſel it pleaſeth him for the advancement of his own glory, the good of his people, and the confuſion of his ſubtileſt adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, making them in the midſt of their joy and triumph, to dig thoſe pits for their own ruine, which they intended for the deſtruction of others, and giving the prize from their great wiſdom, unto the ſimplicity of fooliſh and imprudent people.</p>
               <p>There we may admire him in <hi>the might of his power, making the weak things of the world to confound the mighty;</hi> carrying on a poor
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106523:56"/>ſcattered and peeled people, a poor diſarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, perſecuted Church furniſhed with their prayers and tears, and deſtitute of all outward ſtrength, in defiance of all the power and wiſdom of the world that was againſt it, as in the times of the primitive Church, wherein the Church and Goſpel being born upon the wings of the divine Power and Providence, without the help of outward force or wiſdom by the miniſtry of weak and diſarmed people, as to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward weapons, preſſed through the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and ſtrength of the greateſt Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, and their Armies, through the Schools and reaſonings of the great Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, through fire and fagot, through moſt exquiſite torments and diſgraces, through all that Earth and Hell could do againſt them; and ran through <hi>Europe, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Africa</hi> in a ſmall time, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued the world to the acknowledgment and worſhip of a crucified Saviour, and (which encreaſeth the wonder) ſuffering the ſame Church when once grown proud, hrough a luxurious diet ſhe had put out like a wen, the monſtrons exuberancy of a fleſhly arm, to loſe by ſtrength what ſhe got in weakneſs, which after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſad experiments of the ill ſucceſs of the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106523:56"/>adventure of warlike Chriſtians, with any other weapons then their own before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, may well make us wiſh as one of elder times. <hi>That Christians would lay down their ſwords and spears and return to their prayers and tears;</hi> The loſs of ſo great a part of the world, as the Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans of ſeveral ſorts, and others can boaſt of, being the ſad conſequent of the change of their armory.</p>
               <p>There we may ſee the juſtice of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving ſinners from the mark where a long flight from purſuing vengeance had lighted them down, (they have thought) in-a ſure ſhelter, and fetching them up again out of their darkeſt Corners, and meting unto wickedneſs in its own very meaſure, and making impiety its own judge and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutioner,<note place="margin">Note that blood hath a hot ſcent and ſuch as will not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be gone.</note> and cauſing evill and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on like a well-noſed Blood-hound, to hunt the violent man to overthrow him, to hunt him out of all his windings, and doublings, his traverſes, and buſhes, to bring him unto ruine.</p>
               <p>There we may ſolace our drooping ſouls with the raviſhing beauties of his tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentholineſs, of his unchangeable truth, and of his magnificent bounty overflowing the whole world, and all the creatures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, opening, extending, and enlarging his,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:106523:57"/>arms and breaſts both to the juſt and to the unjuſt; from the higheſt and greateſt Angel to the ſmalleſt worm, or flie, or mite in the whole world, feeding the hands that fight againſt him, nouriſhing thoſe mouthes that blaſpheme and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach him, purſuing thoſe with bleſſings that run away from him in their ſins: Courting thoſe with the kinde tokens and large preſents of his love, that continue in a perverſe reſolution of war and enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt him; begging at the doors of poor and indigent people with great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, that they may receive the free almes of his riches; bearing many and many repulſes and affronts offered unto his kindneſs by proud and wilful duſt and aſhes, and after much long-ſuffering vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating the honor of his deſpiſed good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by turning all his contemned clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy into rage and fury againſt them that reject it.</p>
               <p>And there we may ſolace our ſouls with the ſweet operations of his moſt dear and melting mercies and compaſſions (as in the preſent caſe) unto poor loſt ſinners, fetching them home from their errors and wickedneſs upon the Shoulders of his ſtrength, and in the Boſom of his love, <hi>carrying his Lambs in his arms, and gently <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:106523:57"/>Tremelius</hi> in the Tranſlation of the Old Teſtament, <hi>That he was not converted to be heartily a Chriſtian untill the firſt words of St.</hi> Johns <hi>Goſpel were offered unto him by a ſtrange Providence, as he conceived.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things I hope may ſerve for the juſtification of our fore-mentioned Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of ſome ſucceeding Paſſages after this forementioned work of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in order to the Turks Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and of his conſenting and earneſt deſire to be Baptized.</head>
               <p>GOd having put the Dream, and that work of his Providence which have occaſioned ſo large a Diſcourſe, as two wheels as it were, unto the Chariot of our motions and endeavors, after ſome little pauſe cauſed by the buſineſs of the Lords Day, wherein I was employed, as I have been ſundry times by the favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able admiſſion of reverend Dr. <hi>Bernard</hi> in the honorable Society of <hi>Grayes-Inn</hi> in <hi>London;</hi> which gave a ſeaſonable oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:106523:58"/>to Mr. <hi>Dandulo</hi> to ruminate upon the former paſſages, and to digeſt thoſe admonitions and inſtructions which he had received: Upon the Monday fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing I thought good to endeavor ſome farther promotion of the Work, that we might not ſuffer thoſe heats which God had raiſed to cool in his heart, nor thoſe impreſſions which our Convert had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, to languiſh or grow dull in his Soul, but that we might make a ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able advantage of thoſe encouragments which God had given unto the buſineſs, and ſtrike, as they ſay, which the iron was hot; and preſs in upon his Spirit at that door which God had now begun thus far to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen unto us; and that not onely becauſe conſtancy and prudent ſpeed, that allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as little delay or intermiſſion as may ſtand with convenience, are a great means to ſecure the ſucceſs of a good enterprize, operations being then moſt ſtrong and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous, when they are carried on in a ſort together, ſo that they communicate mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſtrength unto one another, and thoſe that ſucced become powerful, whilſt they make advantage not onely of their own ſtrength but of the force and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the former that have gone immediately before them: Upon which
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:106523:58"/>account it cometh to paſs that ſo many great and good undertakings in the World and in the Church have been loſt by interruptions and procraſtinations; opportunities once loſt, being uſually with much difficulty or not at all to be recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but beſides theſe conſiderations we had reaſon enough to believe that the Devil who is very watchful to take all advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for the blaſting of thoſe purpoſes that are good and holy, would be ready and diligent to make an evil uſe of all the time that ſhould be given him for ſpoiling and diſappointment of that buſineſs we had in hand, whereby God was like to be ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently glorified, if it ſhould obtain our happy and deſired ſucceſs. And that which was indeed very urgent in the requiring a ſpeedy and vigorous proſecution of the work, was the danger that ſeemed to threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten an entire overthrow both unto our endeavors and hopes if not ſpeedily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred, by reaſon of thoſe inclinations that appeared in him of a ſuddain depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not onely from the place where the work was now begun upon him, but out of this Nation, by a return into his own Country, to which purpoſe (as it hath been ſince ſuggeſted with ſome appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, as it ſeemed to me, of diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:106523:59"/>to him and his Converſion; though I cannot ſee upon what reaſon or ground, and as he himſelf hath confeſſed, being put unto the queſtion upon occaſion of the aforeſaid ſuggeſtion unto me) he had attempted an addreſs by way of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition unto the Protector for a Paſs, and ſome proviſion to convey him over into his own Country again.</p>
               <p>And give me leave to take notice of it by the way, becauſe (as I formerly, in ſome diſcourſe that I had with a worthy perſon concerning the care that ought to be taken of this new Convert, upon the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of the great malice that Satan bears unto ſuch performances, againſt which he rageth in himſelf and his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as a Bear robbed of her Whelps, did take upon me to conjecture and aver that it would fall out) there have been various endeavors both to corrupt and to blaſt the credit of the Work that hath been by Gods mercy wrought upon this our Convert. One having reported, and he a Miniſter of theſe times, as I am informed, moſt falſely and uncharitably, that he was hired to become a Chriſtian: Another, that he ſtaieth here and becomes a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, becauſe he dares not return home for fear of being put to death, for violating
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:106523:59"/>the Laws of Mahomet in drinking wine before his converſion, for which he was reproved and threatned by the Agent with whom he came hither from <hi>Algeir:</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other that he was baptized heretofore elſewhere. But I would adviſe all men to take heed how they go about to diſparage the gracious works of the Almighty, through the envy that they bear towards the inſtruments which God is pleaſed to uſe and own in ſuch matters, or to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage young Converts that are brought home into Chriſts Boſom; leſt they prove themſelves thereby to be worſe Chriſtians then he, and render themſelves liable to that condemnation of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.6. <hi>Who ſo ſhall offend one of theſe little ones that beleeve in me</hi> (which may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of thoſe that are children in grace, as of thoſe that are children in years alſo) <hi>it were better for him that a milſtone were hanged about his neck, and that he were drowned in the depth of the Sea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But indeed this intention of his return which he manifeſted ſo clearly by his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of petitioning the Protector for the purpoſe, as is before declared, which hath been alſo urged againſt him as a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement, doth confute the moſt of theſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106523:60"/>ſuggeſtions, and doth render it improbable that he was either afraid to return, or that he was baptized before at any other place; which if it had been true, he could not have returned without an eminent danger of being put to death. And indeed this intention and inclination of his to a ſudden return home, as it hath by Gods Providence proved uſeful for the clearing of him from thoſe falſe accuſations and diſparagements, ſo was it alſo for the haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening us on in the proſecution of the work of his Converſion we had in hand, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whereunto, I made ſpeed unto the purſuance thereof, the day before-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned: And whereas many good under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings it may be feared come ſhort of an happy iſſue, through that evill ſelfiſhneſs which is in too many, whereby they ſeek to get the glory of the work unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, together with that evil confidence and ſelf-conceit which ſome men have of their own abilities which render them averſe from either deſiring or admitting that help that they might have from the Aſſociation of others, which the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves diſdained not to make uſe of: That therefore this work might not want either countenance or aſſiſtance, nor fail through the weakneſs or miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106523:60"/>of my endeanors, of which indeed I was very fearful, whereby I might have become anſwerable for the loſs of his Soul, and for the diſappointment of that glory which hath ſince by his converſion accrued unto God, I prevailed with reverend Dr. <hi>Bernard,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> to accompany me that day unto <hi>Chelſey,</hi> who willingly complied with my deſires therein; and ſent withal to deſire Mr. <hi>Gunning,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Samois</hi> the Interpreter to meet us there. When I with thoſe two reverend Divines firſt mentioned had arrived at the place, Signior <hi>Dandulo</hi> was prevailed with to give us a meeting at my houſe; but Mr. <hi>Gunning</hi> and the Interpreter being not yet come, and the reverend perſons that were with me being unwilling to ſtay long by reaſon of ſome occaſions which it ſeemeth called them back unto <hi>London:</hi> We as well as we could, without the Interpreter enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon ſome diſcourſe with him, which although it was but ſhort, and much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantaged for want of Language; yet we prevailed ſo far, that it obtained ſome kinde of conſent unto the truth of thoſe things which were offered unto him in order to his imbracement of the Chriſtian Religion. (An account of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and diſcourſes that paſſed in this
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:106523:61"/>buſineſs from the beginning to the end, I have thought good to make the buſineſs of a Chapter by it ſelf, to avoid the trouble of repeating over and over the ſame things again both unto my ſelf and to the Reader.) And although we could not as yet obtain of him a declaration of his full reſolution to be baptized, which as he had manifeſted in former communications, he deſired not to be over-haſtily preſſed unto, but that he might be allowed good time to deliberate and conſider of ſo weighty a buſineſs as that was, and that was to be reſolved on no other terms but the deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and forſaking of ſo many earthly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, as of Parents, Country, Inheritance, and Marriage intended, which were all to be drowned unto him in the water of his Baptiſm; yet we obtained this expreſſion of approbation and conſent, at leaſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the main of our diſcourſe, <hi>E Buono,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>This is good or true.</hi> But after our departure back to <hi>London,</hi> the ſame day it pleaſed God to ſend reverend Mr. <hi>Gunning</hi> and the Interpreter unto him, who in my abſence accoſted him with ſome freſh diſcourſes at the Lady <hi>Lawrences,</hi> where was his uſual abode in <hi>Chelſey,</hi> and after ſome ſtrugglings, obtained from him at length (as if ſome violent beam of light
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:106523:61"/>and grace had broken in upon his Soul, and had upon the ſudden captivated all his contrary imaginatious, and ſcattered the miſt of all his waverings and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings) not onely a conſent to be baptized into Chriſtianity, but alſo ſo earneſt a deſire and inclination thereunto, that over-powered all his former thoughts of deliberation; and was ſo impatient of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, that he cried out upon the ſudden <hi>De main,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Let it be done to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row;</hi> and when for the ſolemnity of the performance, and for the obtaining of ſome convenient ſpace and opportunity for his further inſtruction and preparation to that great work, it was made known unto him that it was not thought conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to perform the celebration until the Lords Day; he ſeemed to be ſomething troubled at the delay. The happy and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful news of this bleſſed ſucceſs was careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and very reſpectfully ſent by Mr. <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> unto me at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> which drew me from thence unto <hi>Chelſey</hi> very late at night, that I might be a joyful witneſs of ſo happy an iſſue which God had given unto that gracious work he had begun by ſo weak and inconſiderable an inſtrument as I acknowledge my ſelf to be: And that I might be ſerviceable by ſuch advice, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:106523:62"/>further aſſiſtance as God ſhould enable me to give in order to the accompliſhment of this ſo comfortable a product of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable and excellent mercy of the Lord, to whom be all the glory of this, and all the works of his gracious goodneſs: And if we glory in any thing, let it be in this, that God is pleaſed to be glorified by us or in us, that ſo if we glory we may glory in the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of the Advantages found even in the Religion of the Mahometans, and in the Turks own acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgements, for the carrying on of his Converſion.</head>
               <p>ALthough we have obtained one great end of our Narrative in that declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which hath been already made of that bleſſed ſucceſs which God gave unto our endeavors, in that ready conſent and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire which was wrought in the Soul of our Convert, in ſo little a time as was that of very few weeks, to renounce that
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:106523:62"/>great Impoſtor Mahomet with his delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and to devote and marry his Soul unto Chriſt Jeſus the great and true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the Church and onely Saviour of the World, which is a matter that cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth the joy both of Angels in Heaven, and all good men upon Earth; yet foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as there is an holy, and not onely harmleſs but profitable curioſity, that doth uſually poſſeſs the hearts of Gods people to ſearch (as God is pleaſed to allow them) into the great and gracious works of the Almighty; and not onely to put that que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Num.</hi> 23.23. <hi>What hath God wrought?</hi> That they may ſolace themſelves with the ſpectacle of the ſweetneſs of his mercy, but to look alſo into the ways and means, the manner and method whereby the Lord carries on his performances, that they may delight and edifie their Souls, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of his divine wiſdom and power ſhining forth through the weakneſs and ſimplicity of the inſtruments that he is pleaſed to make uſe of; The holy ſtudy of Gods works being the great Philoſophy of Gods people; and their great learning to underſtand the loving kindneſs of the Lord: That this knowledge may be the fuel and furniture of their praiſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, which is the great end of their
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:106523:63"/>Creation and Redemption, which is the ſtudy that they are invited unto in this Treatiſe; the deſign whereof is to preſent unto them a great and new work, and freſh frame and platform of divine, and thoſe very remarkable diſpenſations which the Lord was pleaſed to produce and put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this ſubject we have in hand. For this reaſon, and yet moreover, becauſe it may perhaps give ſome light not unuſeful for the diſcovery of the great difference there is between the beautiful truths of the Goſpel, and the deformed errors of the Alcoran, and may afford ſome help and encouragement unto others for, and in the undertaking of the like endeavors of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion: I ſhall therefore for the better clearing of the matter, and that men may ſee by what advantages this was, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch like converſions may be attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and know in ſome meaſure from what deſperate errors and miſchief this conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hath brought the Soul of him that hath imbraced it, to the enlargement of our comfort, and advancement of the glory of Gods grace, I ſhall endeavor to ſet down ſome principal matters or tenets wherein the Mahometans and we do agree; and ſubjoyn ſome of thoſe moſt remak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able errors wherein they differ from
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:106523:63"/>Chriſtianity; that by this we may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to diſcover the diſeaſe of thoſe that are miſled in that way of error, and by that we may be the better inſtructed for their converſion; for ſince every conviction doth proceed <hi>à conceſſis,</hi> and muſt fetch its ſtrength from ſome Truths that are granted and agreed upon; if it be rightly managed it is of great concernment for us to know both wherein they agree with us, &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they differ from us, that we may gain ſtrength and advantage from the one, for confutation and remedy of the other. Take therefore theſe Obſervations out of <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Warnerus</hi> in his <hi>Compendium Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> printed at <hi>Leyden,</hi> 1643. and others.</p>
               <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Quod illi (Adam &amp; Eva) cum eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent origo hominum eorum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſtirps, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putati ſint ac ſi homines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> univerſi eſſent.</note> They do acknowledge the fall of all Mankinde in <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> their firſt Parents, in a greater degree I fear then ſome Chriſtians in our daies; for they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare concerning the caſting out of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> out of <hi>Paradiſe</hi> that it may alſo be fitly underſtood of their poſterity; for that ſeeing they were the orignal and root or ſtock of men, they were reputed as if they had been all men in general. In which words ſaith <hi>Warnerus,</hi> the ſame ſeemeth to be intimated that the Apoſtle of the Gentiles ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:106523:64"/>
                  <hi>By one man ſin came into the world— for that or in whom all have ſinned:</hi> So that they ſeem to embrace that of the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>that by the diſobedience of one man many were made ſinners,</hi> but then though they acknowledge the diſeaſe ſo far; yet as evil and unkinde Phyſitians to themſelves and others, they reject the remedy, and will not embrace that which the Apoſtle addeth, <hi>ſo by the obedience of one ſhall many be made righteous;</hi> but inſtead of this they believe that <hi>Adam</hi> without any ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on preſently obtained pardon, when being led by repentance he made this Prayer to God, which the Alcoran reciteth, <hi>Domine noſter, injurii fuimus animabus noſtris, &amp; ſi non condonaveris nobis ac miſertus fueris, damnum feremus. O Lord, we have been injurious to our ſouls, and if thou pardon us not we muſt bear the damage or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And they ſay, that this ſin of our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents was but aſmal ſin, that the puniſhment thereof might be the more exemplary, that men might thereby know that great and careful caution is to be uſed that they let not looſe the bridle unto ſin. <hi>Cum ille Adam ejectus ſit de Paradiſo ob unicum peccatum, quomodo ingrediatur eam plurimis obnoxius peccatis? Since Adam was caſt out of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:106523:64"/>for one ſin, how ſhall he enter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into that is guilty of many ſins?</hi> But they think that there is no need of a Mediator who ſhould expiate this ſin, or that ſhould ſuffer death, that man under his conduct might triumph over death, being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued and chained up.</p>
               <p>They allow Chriſt to be the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> and becauſe Children are denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from their Fathers not from their Mothers, they ſay we may learn from that denomination of him from his Mother, that he was born without a Father, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that expreſſion of the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>She brought forth her Son.</hi> And to thoſe eminent Propheſies, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. where he is called the <hi>Seed of the woman,</hi> not of the man. And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.14. where he is promiſed to be the Son of a Virgin: And ſuch a wonderful concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and birth they acknowledge this to be as never was granted unto any other Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Childe; and therefore in their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the words which they ſay the Angel ſpake unto the Virgin, <hi>O Maria, Dius elegit te &amp; purificavit te, elegit te ſupra mulieres omnis aevi, &amp;c. O Mary, God hath choſen thee and purified thee, he hath choſen thee above the women of all Ages.</hi> They in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret it thus, He hath purified thee from
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:106523:65"/>impure works, and from that of which the Jews accuſed thee, he hath choſen thee above women of all ages, in that he gave thee <hi>Jeſus</hi> without a Father, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened not unto any other amongſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; contrary to that wicked lie of the Jews in their <hi>Sepher Juchafin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> when they ſay that in the reign of the Grecians, and the time of the Tribes, there was a famous wiſe man at <hi>Rome,</hi> called <hi>Prometheuss</hi> who decreed that the Ring ſhould be worn up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the fourth finger, becauſe the vain of the heart was in it and that he had a Son called <hi>Antaros,</hi> who alſo was a man of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent wiſdom, and that he had ſeven daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whereof one was named <hi>Eſchtoniphos,</hi> who as the Gentiles report brought forth two ſons, <hi>Ephun</hi> and <hi>Schaltſebin,</hi> and that ſhe was a Virgin before and after her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and that was heard ſaith the Author. Whereunto was added by the hand-writing of a certain Jew in the copy that was in <hi>Warnerus</hi> his hands,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as he relateth; it is hard to the Chriſtians, being againſt their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who ſay this was a miracle in <hi>Mary,</hi> the Mother of Jeſus. The Turks alſo ſay ſome of them that <hi>Mary</hi> conceived at the thirteenth year of her age, others at the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:106523:65"/>tenth; and ſome ſay that ſhe was deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſixth moneth, others in the ſeventh moneth, others in the eighth moneth, <hi>nec ſupervixit partus octavo menſe editus praeterquam beatus Jeſus;</hi> and that never any birth brought forth in the eighth month lived, but only the bleſſed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. They ſay alſo that he was brought forth under a Palm-tree; and they further ſay, That God created one without Father or Mother, as <hi>Adam,</hi> and brought forth one of a Mother without a Father, as <hi>Jeſus;</hi> &amp; that <hi>Joſeph</hi> having a ſuſpition of her thought to have killed her; that the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed, ſaying That ſhe was with childe by the Holy Ghoſt, and ſo hindered him</p>
               <p>They ſay alſo that <hi>Mary</hi> was the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Amran,</hi> the Son of <hi>Matan,</hi> the Son of <hi>Suliman,</hi> the Son of <hi>David,</hi> the Son of <hi>Jeſſe;</hi> and that between this <hi>Amran</hi> and that <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> which was the Father of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> there paſſed a thouſand &amp; eighty years; and that ſhe was brought up by <hi>Zacharias,</hi> and that her food was ſent down unto her from Paradiſe; ſo that ſhe never ſucked any Breaſt, but that ſhe had ſent her from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven winter fruits in Summer, and ſummer fruits in Winter; and that as often as <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias</hi> went unto her in the Temple, he found meat by her: and when he asked her whence ſhe had it; ſhe ſaid that it was
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:106523:66"/>from God, for God feedeth whom he will without meaſure; and that many were found perfect amongſt men, but none a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt women, but onely Four, <hi>Aſia</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Meraham, Mary</hi> the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Amran, Chadiga</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Hubald,</hi> and <hi>Fatima</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Mahomet;</hi> and that <hi>Mary</hi> was conſecrated unto God, whilſt ſhe was yet in the womb.</p>
               <p>But though they acknowledg Chriſt to be the Son of the Virgin, yet they wickedly deny his Divinity; they ſay that Chriſt was born a Servant as other Servants; they alſo deny him to be the Son of God. The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſay they, made him the Son of God. But Jeſus is only a Servant, ſay they, as other Servants, and they ſeem to bring in God ſpeaking thus; We have dealt graciouſly with him, (that is with Jeſus) in that we have appointed him to be a wonder, in that we have created him without an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termediate or ſecond cauſe, as we created <hi>Adam,</hi> and rendered him famous by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie; but they conclude againſt his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, becauſe he knows not all that God knoweth, through ignorance of the divine myſtery of his Incarnation, and of the unconfounded propriety of the two Natures in Chriſt. And though they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that Chriſt did miracles, as that he cleanſed the Lepers, and raiſed the dead,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:106523:66"/>yet they ſay he did them not by his own power, but by the power of God; and ſo they ſay he reſtored <hi>Sem</hi> the Son of <hi>Noab</hi> to life. The ground upon which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſt to be God, is, becauſe they ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly ſuppoſe the Unity of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature cannot be preſerved if Chriſt ſhould be acknowledged to be God: Therefore they have that ſo often in their Alcoran, and other Writings, ſaith <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Non eſt Deus niſi ille,</hi> There is no God but he; And amongſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things that are required unto their Faith, the firſt is this confeſſion that there is not any God but one, which is indeed a great truth acknowledged by the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church; but they ignorantly oppoſe it to the Trinity of perſons, being bound up in the dark Dungeon of their carnal and weak reaſon; and therein they agree with the <hi>Socinians</hi> and <hi>Photinians,</hi> which are indeed rather Turks then Chriſtians: The Turks themſelves having as high an opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt as they, and they as low an opinion of him as the Turks.</p>
               <p>They ſay moreover that Chriſt doth not arrogate this honor to himſelf, to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Son of God; but in the day of the Reſurrection he will teſtifie againſt the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:106523:67"/>Jews for that they charged him with falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and againſt the Chriſtians for calling him the Son of God.</p>
               <p>They confeſs indeed, That the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans teach but One Eſſence but Three perſons; and they ſay that by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Father, the Chriſtians under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Eſſence; by that of the Son, Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; by that of the Holy Ghoſt, Life: which the Alcoran underſtandeth, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Commentary, as if God, Chriſt, and <hi>Mary</hi> were Three Gods; and Chriſt the Son of God by <hi>Mary;</hi> obſerve how they are held in their errors and oppoſition to Chriſtianity, by their groſs miſtakes of the Chriſtian Doctrine.</p>
               <p>The grounds of this their denial of the divine generation or Sonſhip of Chriſt, whereby he is the Son of God, are theſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1. A carnal conceit that nothing can generate but a Body; for generation, ſay they, is the property of Bodies.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That Generation is not but between equals of the ſame kinde; but God, ſay they, in regard of his great Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy hath no Equal or Conſort, nor can have; becauſe if he had any Conſort, that Conſort muſt be from the ſame kinde, but God acknowledgeth no kinde.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:106523:67"/>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe there is nothing that he hath not created, and which he hath not known; and therefore he wanted no Son. Thus they doat that value God a according to the Creature.</p>
               <p>Yet they give unto Chriſt the name of <hi>Meſſias,</hi> which they ſay is one of the moſt noble titles, derived from the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which they interpret <hi>Benedictus,</hi> or the <hi>Bleſſed;</hi> whereas indeed it ſignifieth the <hi>Anointed,</hi> the ſame which <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſignifieth in the Greek Tongue, implying the three annointed Offices of Chriſt; the great High Prieſt; the great Prophet, and the great King of the Church.</p>
               <p>They acknowledg him alſo by the name <hi>Jeſus,</hi> which they ſay is a barbarous name or word that cannot be expounded or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted, which in the Syriack Tongue is <hi>Jeſchua,</hi> but they are ignorant that this name given him from Heaven ſignifieth the <hi>Savior,</hi> from the <hi>root</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to <hi>ſave</hi> in the Hebrew Tongue, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Greek alſo ſignifieth an <hi>Healer,</hi> or <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <hi>heal,</hi> which in the Saxon accordingly is uſually tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Haeleno, in the Saxon <hi>Goſpels,</hi> as I remember; wherein is implied that great myſtery which thoſe blinded people ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge not, that is, that this Jeſus is
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:106523:68"/>the great Saviour and ſpiritual Phyſitian both of Jews, and Greeks, or Gentiles; having that name given him by the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful providence of God, that ſignifieth a Saviour and a Healer in both Languages; an importance, the like whereof I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded will hardly be found in ſuch a wonderful compliance of Languages in any other name in the world, where the roots from whence it is derived have no derivation from one another.</p>
               <p>They confeſs that he was ſent from God, that he might be the proclaimer of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and the Corrector or Reformer of humane pravity, or the wickedneſs of man, a Teacher of righteouſneſs and a Publiſher of the Goſpel, and they do maintain that he executed his Office faithfully, in that he preached but one God, and converted men from their impious and vain wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, to know and worſhip the true God.</p>
               <p>They do unanimouſly declare that he wrought many miracles, reſtoring ſtrength to the weak, health to the ſick, opening the eyes of the blinde, purging away the blemiſhes of defiled bodies, raiſing the dead unto life again, as if they had been awaked out of ſleep, though they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge not that immortal power in him
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:106523:68"/>whereby he performed theſe things, as an argument of his Divinity.</p>
               <p>They allow him the Title of the Word of God; ſo the Alcoran brings in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels thus ſpeaking unto the Virgin, <hi>O Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, God doth declare unto thee his WORD, his name is Chriſt:</hi> And they ſay that Chriſt was ſtiled by that name, becauſe he was not born but of the onely Word of God; the manner thereof they thus expreſs, God ſaid, <hi>be thou without the help of Father.</hi> In the aſcribing this name unto Chriſt, they agree ſo far with that of <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1. <hi>In the beginning was the Word,</hi> though they reject the true ſence and meaning of that title, implying the divine perſon of Chriſt: they ſay alſo that he is <hi>ſermo verus Dei,</hi> The true Word of God. So the Alcoran, <hi>This Jeſus is the true Word or Speech, whom the Jews call an Impoſter and a Lyar, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians the Son of God;</hi> he is called alſo by them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>The Spirit of God;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as they interpret, he hath the Spirit that floweth like ſeed from the living Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe he is indeed brought forth of God, and by his abſolute power; though they give that title alſo unto the Angel <hi>Gabriel,</hi> as the Commentary intepret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that place of the Alcoran, <hi>We ſent to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:106523:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>her,</hi> that is to <hi>Mary, our Spirit, that is Gabriel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They ſay alſo that Chriſt is the Apoſtle of God, which is indeed a great Office of Chriſt, that ſeems ſpecially to be foretold in that name <hi>Shiloh, Miſſas,</hi> or <hi>Sent,</hi> as it may be interpreted, and is intimated by our Saviour in ſeveral places of Scripture, where he is ſaid to be ſent of the Father; for <hi>Apostolus,</hi> or Apoſtle, is derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to <hi>ſend;</hi> which I mention for the ſake of thoſe that are ignorant of ſo ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary a matter, ſo that it ſignifieth one ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſent, and in ſacred uſe, one ſent to teach and govern the people of God, in order to Goſpel-Truth, Grace, and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. This Office of Chriſt we have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly and eminently mentioned, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>And this is it which he hath derived from himſelf unto the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors in the Church; <hi>As my Father hath ſent me, ſo ſend I you:</hi> This Office is at leaſt in the name acknowledged by the Turks, and yet as it is thought is too too much ſlighted in the ſucceſſion thereof by too many Chriſtians, that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the Apoſtles Succeſſors, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Government of the Church; I wiſh they that have power in this Nation would conſider of this matter, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:106523:69"/>it in their publick conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>The Turks acknowledge Chriſt the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle of God, but they do not honor him nor advance him in the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Office as they ſhould, ſince they ranck him in a fort with other Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates or Prophets, <hi>Chriſtus filius Mariae,</hi> ſay they, <hi>non eſt niſi Legatus ante quem jam alii venerunt Legati;</hi> Chriſt the Son of <hi>Mary</hi> is but an Ambaſſador before whom other Ambaſſadors have already come. And his condition in revelation, ſay they, is like the condition of the reſt of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that have gone before. Revelation ſay they is, <hi>Sermo occultus qui cito fit:</hi> An hidden ſpeech coming ſuddenly; and this they ſay is of three ſorts: 1. By Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unto which Dreams are referred. 2. By a Voice or Call. 3. Or by a Legate or Angel. In the firſt manner God, they ſay. ſpake to <hi>Abraham.</hi> In the ſecond to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſo unto the Angels themſelves, which kinde the Alcorn calls <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>poſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> behinde the Hanging or Curtain, where a voice is heard, but the ſpeaker not ſeen; for none, ſay they, hath ſeen God, and therefore they ſay that neither <hi>Moſes</hi> nor <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaw God.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:106523:70"/>
               <p n="3">3. By the ſending of an Angel: As God ſpake unto the other Prophets beſide <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> unto whom, they ſay, he ſpake imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, as to an Angel. To Chriſt, they ſay, he ſpake as unto the reſt of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets by an Angell. And they ſay the Goſpel was ſent him from Heaven with the teſtimony of Miracles, and amongſt the reſt they ſay he made a Bird of clay, and inſpired it with life. And they ſay Jeſus was famous in this life by Propheſie, and in the other life by interceſſion, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation of degree ia Paradiſe, that he might be amongſt thoſe that ſtand before the Throne, and a companion of Angels. So they hold Chriſt to be an Interceſſor for the godly. Whoſoever readeth <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for him Jeſus hath prayed for the forgiveneſs of his ſins; as long as he liveth in this world, and at the laſt day he is his companion</p>
               <p>They acknowledge the day of Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which they call the day of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</p>
               <p>But though they thus exalt Chriſt in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, yet they ſay Mahomet is much more exalted in the other life, being honored or celebrated by the Angels, together with God, and that four of them ſay, <hi>Praiſe
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:106523:70"/>be to thee, O God, and to thy Mahomet; Praiſe be to thee for thy Clemency after thy Power.</hi> And four ſay, <hi>Praiſe be to thee, O God, and to thy Madomet. for thy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs after thy Wiſdom.</hi> Thus they doat and rave.</p>
               <p>They ſay that Chriſt was taken up to Heaven, but Mahomet is more excellent, who was ſent unto men in general, and to whom ſins were forgiven, both which he committed before, and which he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards committed; as if God had given Mahomet a diſpenſation to commit ſin: Mark the the Impiety and Blaſphemy of this ſaying. And they ſay that Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met concluded the number of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</p>
               <p>They ſay that Chriſt was preſently heard as often as he called upon God. And they have a ſtrange ſtory of a Table, and a Fiſh broiled that was ſent down from Heaven to him and his Apoſtles at his prayer, and that he revived the fiſh, and turned it preſently again into a broiled fiſh, and that the Table afterward vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; And that the Apoſtles when they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards rebelled, were turned into Apes and Swine.</p>
               <p>They ſay as the Law was given to <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Pſalms to <hi>David,</hi> ſo the Goſpel to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:106523:71"/>
                  <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that it was ſent from Heaven the Thirteenth day of <hi>Ramdan,</hi> as the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coran was ſent down the Twenty fourth day of that moneth. They ſay that God exalted <hi>Ramdan</hi> amongſt the Moneths, and <hi>Friday</hi> amongſt the Days, becauſe the Sun roſe upon that day; and <hi>Adam</hi> was created and caſt out into the Earth upon that day, and that the Day of Judgment ſhall be upon that day.</p>
               <p>They ſay, which is very obſervable for the converſion of Turks, that Mahomet confirmed the Law and the Goſpel, and commanded to believe the truth of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and whatever (of Books) was ſent down unto them; and that in the Goſpel there is the right way, light, and inſtruction for the godly; and they profeſs to believe whatſoever is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Law and Goſpel. Thus we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in God, and that that was ſent down to <hi>Abraham, Iſmael, Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> and the Tribes; and that was delivered to <hi>Moſes,</hi> to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and to the Prophets from God; and we make no difference between any of them, ſo as leſs to believe them.</p>
               <p>But they ſay falſely that the Goſpel hath been changed, for they ſay that the name of Mahomet was in the Law and in the Goſpel. And in their Hiſtories they ſay,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:106523:71"/>that his name was alſo in the Pſalms, and this they ſay a certain Monk confeſſed; and that Jeſus foretold the coming of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet and his people.</p>
               <p>They ſay that <hi>Abraham</hi> profeſſed their Religion under the name of <hi>Iſlamiſm</hi> long before the Law and the Goſpel, and that he was neither Jew nor Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>They deny that Chriſt truly died, but they ſay that he was without death tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into Heaven. See their impudence againſt ſo manifeſt a truth. They ſay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that the Jews were deceived, and thought they had ſlain Chriſt, but they ſlew him not; but that God took him up unto himſelf. And that when the Jews were about to kill Chriſt, he asked his Companions, Which of you will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to have my likeneſs put upon him, that ſo he may go into Paradiſe? and that one of them ſaid, <hi>I will,</hi> and that God preſently put the Image of Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and that he was ſlain and crucified inſtead of Chriſt; and that after this the Aſſociates of Chriſt fell at diſſention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this; and that ſome ſaid Chriſt was God and could not die, others that he was killed and crucified, others, if Jeſus were crucified where is our Companion? if our Companion was crucified, where is
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:106523:72"/>then Jeſus? Others ſaid, he was taken up into Heaven.</p>
               <p>They hold that Jeſus ſhall deſcend from Heaven in the laſt days, and that there ſhall be no people to whom the Book comes (<hi>i.e.</hi> I conceive the Alcoran, which they call <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as we the Scriptures, the Bible) but they ſhall believe in it: So that there ſhall be but one Religion, to wit, <hi>Iſlamiſm,</hi> and God at that time ſhall ſlay the falſe Meſſiah, and there ſhall be ſafety, ſo that the Lions ſhall eat with the Camels, the Leopards with the Oxen, Wolves with the Sheep, and Children ſhall play with Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents</p>
               <p>And they ſay Chriſt ſhall ſtay and dwell upon earth Forty years; and that then the Muſlins or Muſſel-men, <hi>i.e.</hi> the Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans ſhall pray over him. They ſay more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over that when Chriſt ſhall deſcend, he ſhall frame himſelf according to the order of Mahomet, and ſhall poure out prayers turning toward him, as he were one of his followers. Nor ſhall the laſt day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſay they, until the deſcending of Jeſus go before. They hold alſo that other dreadful ſigns ſhall go before the laſt day, The falſe Chriſt or Meſſiah, Gog and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog, and the riſing of the Sun in the Weſt. Hence that irreligious or prophane Jeſt,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:106523:72"/>whereby the witty <hi>Perſian</hi> deciphereth the manners of a libidinous Judge, bringing in the King thus beſpeaking the Judge, and the Judge replying to the King: The King ſaid to the Judge, Riſe I pray you, for the Sun is now riſen; the Judge ſaid, In what part of the world did he riſe? The King anſwered, in the Eaſt, as he is wont. Then ſaid the Judge, Bleſſed be God, for the door is yet open to repentance. I wiſh there were no ſuch preſumptuous ſcoffers amongſt Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> An account of the Arguments uſed for the converſion of the Turk, with ſome illnſtration and enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of his Baptiſm.</head>
               <p>WHoſoever ſhall take but a view of thoſe things that have been diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered concerning the madneſs and vanity of the Mahometan Religion, they would have cauſe enough to wonder that a mete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or made up of ſuch earthy and corrupt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halations ſhould laſt ſo long, &amp; have ſuch a
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:106523:73"/>powerful influence upon the minds of ſuch multitudes of thoſe creatures that have principles of Reaſon and Religion in them, but that the terrors of the World, and carnal apprehenſions and intereſts have ſo embaſed the hearts, and dazled the eies of poor mortals, that moſt men worſhip a flaming Sword, eſpecially when the Hilts of it are enchaſed with tranſitory delights and advantages. And the greateſt part of the world may ſeem to have their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cut out unto them by the weapons of their conquering Subduers, rather then commended unto them by the force of convincing Arguments.</p>
               <p>And indeed were not the ſouls of thoſe that profeſs the Mahometan religion wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up in a dark vail of ignorance, under the cloud whereof they are purpoſely kept, it might ſeem almoſt incredible that they ſhould not eaſily diſclaim ſuch impious er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, the falſhood and impiety whereof are abundantly convinced by the very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play and diſcovery of the very tenets and practiſes themſelves; and yet a very rare thing hath it bin to hear of one bred up in that impoſture of Turciſm, converted to the glorious light of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>It may eaſily be perceived by what hath been delivered, what great advantages
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:106523:73"/>there lie before us, even in the great ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſurdity of their opinions where they are at oppoſition unto us, and in thoſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches that they make toward Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity in ſome other things that they hold, as hath been ſhewed, for the undertaking and promoting their converſion, which will render it the more unanſwerable and unexcuſable, that there have been no more adventurers to that purpoſe: Since the Church which is the illuminated part of the world, as it hath a charge of the great work of the converſion of the reſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of unto that truth which God hath reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto her, not onely for her own ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but alſo for the guidance and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of others, according to that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion which is yet in force, and hath in it the power of a command or heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly injunction from Chriſt, <hi>Go and teach,</hi> or make Diſciples of <hi>all Nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and if there had been but the tenth part of thoſe lives ventured upon a ſuffering account for the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Gods truth, that have been hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and loſt in the bloody quarrels of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, Covetouſneſs and Revenge, and for the propagating of Dominion by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:106523:74"/>of the rights of other Princes and people, in the way of bloody and active violence, in all probability the world ere this time might have been reduced unto the holy Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus, and that Propheſie fulfilled which we yet hope for, (and God may promote it even from ſuch a beginning as this) that in <hi>the laſt days the mountain of the Lords houſe ſhall be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the top of the mountains,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſet above the hills, and all Nations ſhall flow unto it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this is like to be the work rather of the croſs then of the Sword. <hi>In hoc ſigno vinces,</hi> is ſtill the Chriſtians Motto. Our Victories are to be obtained under the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the croſs.</p>
               <p>But that I may draw to a Concluſion; The more then ordinary knowledge that our Convert ſeemed to have obtained not onely of the Turkiſh Religion, but alſo in ſome meaſure of the Chriſtian, by means (as it may be conceived) of his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Mother, gave ſome good advantage to our work.</p>
               <p>The firſt attempt whereof was an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to bring him into ſome good ſenſe of the great concernment of his Soul in the embracement or rejection of the truth,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:106523:74"/>no leſs then in his eternal greateſt good or evill, and to bring him into diſlike, or at leaſt into a doubt of that erroneous and impious way that he embraced, as being uncorreſpondent and unſatisfactory to that which is, and needs muſt be the aim of every wiſe and ſerious man, in the choice or embracement of any Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which is a well grounded hope and ſucceeding attainment of the ſalvation of his Soul in another world, and here in this life the peace of a good Conſcience next to the glory and honour of God, which as it was ſhewed him, could not be found without a remedy for ſin, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed unto Gods wrath and to eternal death and condemnation: And that there could be no remedy for this deadly diſeaſe but by a ſatisfaction to Gods Juſtice, <hi>That Mercy and Truth might meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and Righteouſneſs and Peace might kiſs each other;</hi> which remedy or ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction was not at all offered in that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that he embraced.</p>
               <p>He ſaid that God gave pardon upon repentance; but it was ſhewed him that his repentance, and the repentance of all others was imperfect; and no man was ſo cleared thereby from ſin, but
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:106523:75"/>that there would ſtill need a ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the failings even of repentance and of the beſt ordered life that is to be found amongſt men in this life. That this ſatisfaction is clearly and fully of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in the Chriſtian Religion, in the blood, and ſufferings, and righteouſneſs of Chriſt Jeſus, who being God and Man, and the eternal Son of God, became a fit Mediator between God and Man, and offered himſelf a ſufficient Sacrifice unto the Divine Juſtice for the ſins of the whole World: The benefit whereof, as it is propoſed in the Goſpel unto repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and to all true penitent ſinners, ſo it is to be received onely from and in Chriſt Jeſus, and by the true faith of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Upon this diſcourſe, or to this purpoſe, with ſome other, which I cannot well now remember, he ſeemed to be ſomething ſtartled, and to doubt whether the ground whereon he ſtood was ſound or no: And as I remember expreſſed ſome deſire that God would direct him to the Truth.</p>
               <p>Some further Argumenrs were uſed to diſcover yet further unto him, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the inſufficiency, but the impiety and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:106523:75"/>vanity and great uncertainty of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion he had embraced; as that which countenanced cruelty and oppreſſion, was carried on by violence and carnal ways, and propoſed low and carnal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights for the reward, below the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the ſpiritual Soul of Man; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced wickedneſs, as Impurity and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; and proceeded from a perſon of a carnal and laſcivious temper and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, who pretended a more then ordinary Commiſſion and allowance for luſt, as a priviledge belonging to him as the great Prophet. That pretended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed revelation from Heaven, but had no teſtimony from God to commend it to the Souls of men; but depended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bare aſſertion of Mahomet, which if he be conſidered in the ſingleneſs of his perſon, being a man ſubject to error as well as others; eſpecially if he be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in his laſcivious and wicked qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and condition, is too ſandy a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of more then much too weak a credit, that the venture of the eternal good and ſafety of one ſingle Soul ſhould be committed thereto, much leſs of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny millions, or of the whole world: That it was a Religion ſtuffed with mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:106523:76"/>lies and legends, as may be ſeen by thoſe things that have been ſet down</p>
               <p>Whereas on the other ſide the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion hath upon it the very ſtamp of Gods image, which is his ſeal, in the high, excellent, myſterious and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual wiſdom, too high for humane Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture in any likelihood to invent; ſince it is ſo far too high for humane Wiſdom or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, even ſince it is revealed, to conceive, which is exactly anſwerable and uniform and correſpondent to it ſelf in all the members and parts thereof, which all make up a ſweet and excellent tune and harmony amongſt themſelves, without any jar or diſcord between them; and all the Writers thereof, though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many, and living in many and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Ages and places, were forbidden thereby to conſpire in falſhood with one another; wherein there muſt needs have been much boggling in matters ſo high above humane reaſon and comprehenſion, if there had not been an infallible rule of divine Light and Truth to guide and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite them together at ſo great a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>Beſides the wonderful and excellent
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:106523:76"/>conſent that is between the Types and Propheſies, and the fulfilled events there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: The former whereof are for the moſt part conſigned over unto us by the Jews, profeſſed enemies unto the Chriſtian Truth, who maintain themſelves, and have delivered over unto us the predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the completions whereof yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves now deny: And ſo it is fulfilled of that blinded Nation of the Jews, that is ſaid by one, I know not whom, of them, that it is <hi>Aſinus portanus vinum &amp; bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens aquam, An Aſs that carrieth wine, and drinketh water:</hi> They carry the wine of the holy Propheſies, and drink the water of their own fooliſh and malicious miſ-interpretations and traditions.</p>
               <p>It hath the ſtamp of the Divine wiſdom and goodneſs upon it, in that holy poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy eſtabliſhed in the bond of Divine and Chriſtian Love, whereby it unites all in the love of God, and in a mutual love unto, and a mutual charge of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of all men, even greateſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, in all their concernments, and in holy peace providing for all, and carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on all things with a heavenly and publick ſpirit; ſo that if it were but ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally embraced, it would make the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:106523:77"/>world happy, and eſtabliſh a kinde of Heaven upon Earth; when every man ſhould have a care of another as of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in ſoul and ſpiritual good, in matter of Life, Eſtate, Health. Reputation, and all other matters wherein their good is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, whereby that wicked voice of <hi>Cain,</hi> which crieth ſo loud in the hearts and practices of the world, would be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced and excluded out of the ſociety of mankinde, <hi>Am I my Brothes keeper?</hi> ſince it maketh all men keepers of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and teacheth all to take care of the publike good of all, and thereby enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the riches and content of all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, teaching them to joy and delight in the good and bleſſing of others, as well as their own.</p>
               <p>It hath the ſtamp of Gods Holineſs and Righteouſneſs upon it, in the utter oppoſition that it hath unto all ſin, in the admirable and perfect rules of Juſtice and Piety, and purity which it eſtabliſheth, both in regard of inward motions, thoughts, and affections, and in outward carriage and converſation of life, ſetting up the right mark before us, which is Gods glory, and eternal happineſs in him to be purſued by all, in all thoughts,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:106523:77"/>words, and actions, in all their Offices, Trades and Vocations; ſo bringing in the whole life of man to be an holy ſacrifice to God. And directing us unto this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Goal or prize in the holy road, or way of the holy commands of God, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging and facilitating our obedience thereunto by gracious promiſes, outbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all that the World or the Fleſh, or the Devil can offer to hire us or move us to ſin or wickedneſs, and ſo by another great and holy policy, engrafting our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt into all our duty; ſo that we cannot ſin againſt God, but we muſt ſin againſt our own felicity, nor advance in holineſs but we muſt alſo advance in happineſs, making holineſs and happineſs upon the matter one and the ſame thing, though they ſeem two unto us by the weakneſs of our ſight, as one Candle ſeemeth two unto a diſtempered or weak eye.</p>
               <p>It hath the ſtamp of Gods Meekneſs and Mercy upon it, not onely in revealing it unto us, and pouring it out upon us in the wonderful works of Redemption and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by Chriſt Jeſus, at which the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and hoſt of Heaven ſtand amazed, whilſt wicked and unthankful mortals de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe and contemn it; but in the holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:106523:78"/>which it enjoineth unto all, and worketh in the hearts and practices of true Chriſtians thereunto, forbidding all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and every degree of cruelty and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, of hatred, malice, envy, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge both in the root and the fruit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and enjoining all acts of Mercy and compaſſion towards others, even our greateſt adverſaries and ſtrangers, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever different from us in judgment or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, allowing no hatred unto any thing but ſin, thereby opening a door of love unto the whole world for their edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and bringing in unto Chriſt Jeſus, and to the Truth, Grace and Salvation of the Goſpel, which is too little thought on and leſs practiſed by the new and ſtrange Chriſtians of our days, whom God will convince either to condemnation or to converſion, as may be hoped by ſuch as this our Convert and others whom he ſhall bring home unto his truth and love, making even them to provoke us to jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, and to be not onely Profeſſors with us, but Reformers of us.</p>
               <p>And theſe Rules of Love, Compaſſion, and Mercy are eſtabliſhed in an excellent and moſt exact and perfect order and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod both in regard of the objects and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:106523:78"/>thereof, they being firſt to be regarded that are neareſt and deareſt to God and us, or whoſe preſervation and good is of greateſt or moſt general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment. And the operations to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed as in none but juſt, and pure, and holy, ſo chiefly and ſpecially in ſpiritual ways. And this mark of love and tender compaſſion amongſt Chriſtians was that that made them antiently as glorious in the eyes of God and Man, as the contrary cruelty and unmercifulneſs hath rendred inglorious and ignominious the degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and falſe Chriſtians of our days. So that the very Heathens are ſaid to have fallen into an admiration of their mutual mercy, with an <hi>Ecce quam ſe invicem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligunt, ecce quam pro ſe invicem mori pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati ſunt; Behold how theſe Chriſtians love one another, Behold how theſe Chriſtians are ready to die for one another!</hi> As now Turks and Heathens may cry out with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination againſt the Chriſtians and ſelf Canonizing Saints of our days, <hi>Ecce quam ſe invicem oderint, ecce quam ſe invicem interficere parati ſunt!</hi> it is tranſlated in letters and language of blood, and written all over our age and Nations; <hi>Behold how theſe Chriſtians hate one another, behold
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:106523:79"/>how theſe Chriſtians are ready to kill and deſtroy one another!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This and other wicked practiſes of thoſe that walk under the names of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſo diametrally oppoſite unto the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and merciful rule and conſtitution of Chriſt Jeſus, are thoſe that have caſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach upon the name of Chriſt, and have clouded up the beauty and ſplendor of the Goſpel and the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and do continually blaſt and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the converſion of Jews, Turks, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and others thereunto, who are thereby confirmed and encouraged in their evill ways. For the love of God and our own ſouls let us think upon it. The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed lives of Chriſtians will anſwer for, and be charged with the deſtruction of the reſt of the world as well as for their own, and theirs amongſt whom they live. <hi>But God is true, though every man be a lyar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſtian Religion hath upon it the ſtamp and teſtimony of the great and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemiſhed innocency and piety of Chriſt Jeſus, in the holineſs of his Life and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine acknowledged by the Turks them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>Of the great power of God in his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:106523:79"/>Incarnation, and miraculous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception and birth; whereby he was a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle himſelf above all other miracles whatſoever. The latter whereof, to wit, his wonderful conception and birth is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by the Mahometans them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>In the many and great wonders that he wrought, which they themſelves alſo confeſs it is teſtified unto: As alſo by his Reſurrection from the dead, and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention ineo Heauen, which, to wit his Aſcention, they aver, though they deny his Death and Reſurrection By the voice from Heaven at his Baptiſm and transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. By the deſcending of the Holy Ghoſt both upon himſelf in the form of a Dove, and upon his Diſciples in the form of fiery cloven tongues after his aſcention upon the day of Pentecoſt, to the enduing of them with thoſe wonderful gifts of all Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages which they exerciſed in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of many witneſſes of ſeveral parts and Nations, who by Gods providence were then at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which was then made, as it were, the Repreſentative of the World, that it might be the Theater of ſo glorious a ſpectacle.</p>
               <p>To this may be added the great effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:106523:80"/>and power of the Goſpel grace, ſhining in the lives of true Chriſtians, and in the glorious ſufferings of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</p>
               <p>The ſpiritual and heavenly propoſals of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>And the ſpiritual wayes contrary to humane wiſdom and carnal intereſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out humane force, whereby it hath been carried on.</p>
               <p>And the ſtanding teſtimony that is unto this day, in the diſſipation, and afflicted, and wretched, and hateful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the baniſhed Jewiſh Nation, ſcattered over the world, having been under that judgement for the ſpace of One thouſand ſix hundred years and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, as was foretold by <hi>Daniel,</hi> and our Bleſſed Saviour himſelf, that they may be witneſſes to the world in the ſeveral Nations where they are ſcattered, and againſt themſelves, of the truth of the Goſpel and the glory of Chriſt, whoſe blood is upon them to this day, according to that dreadful curſe that they laid upon themſelves.</p>
               <p>I have been bold to enlarge ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more upon this then I did in the preſſing of it upon the Turk; I hope it
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:106523:80"/>may be for the good of him and others: Now becauſe we found that he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the Law, and Prophets, and the holy Evangeliſts; we had recourſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them for the conviction of him in the Three great points of Chriſtianity, which he oppoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> The God-head of Chriſt, and that he is the Son of God, and that he died and ſatisfied for the ſins of the World, and ſo became the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and Redeemer of Mankinde. He was acquainted therefore by me with ſome paſſages of the Fifty third of <hi>Iſay,</hi> and as I remember with that wonderful Propheſie of the Ninth of <hi>Daniel,</hi> where the death and ſatisfaction of the Meſſiah or Chriſt, are ſo clearly and evangelically expreſſed.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Gunning</hi> purſued the work that was begun with great induſtry, ability, and diligence; ſhewing him that his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion had no warrant of truth in it, having neither the teſtimony from reaſon, not from heavenly revelation, made known by miracles, or any ſuch heavenly evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which give abundant witneſs to the truth of Chriſtianity; and when he vainly pretended, as it ſeems he had been inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that there was a Propheſie in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:106523:81"/>that another people ſhould come to inform the World after the Chriſtians, which it ſeems, was a miſpriſion of that place in <hi>Daniel</hi> 9.26. <hi>The people of the Prince that ſhall come ſhall deſtroy the City and the Sanctuary, &amp;c.</hi> we ſhewed him as I remember, the true interpretation of the place, that it was a Propheſie of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by <hi>Titus Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian,</hi> and the Roman people. And having obtained of him that Chriſt was a true Prophet, and that all that he ſpake was truth, and that the Goſpel of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts was true; The Divinity of Chriſt, and his being the Son of God was proved unto him out of the firſt of <hi>John</hi> the firſt verſe. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if my memory fail not, and out of the words of our Saviour, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared himſelf to be the Son of God. But that that eſpecially prevailed with him was drawn from that acknowledgement that the Mahometans have of Chriſt, that he was the Spirit of God, from whence it was ſhewed him that ſince the Spirit of God could be none other then God himſelf, that Chriſt then muſt needs be God, as the ſpirit of man is principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the man himſelf; which although it is to be warily underſtood, and ſo as not to
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:106523:81"/>make any confuſion between the perſons of Chriſt and the Holy Ghoſt; yet it was <hi>Argumentum ad hominem, ex conceſſo,</hi> and he ſeemed thereby to be convinced of the truth of his Divinity, and of the falſhood and contradiction of the Mahometan Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligon, that acknowledged Chriſt to be the Spirit of God, and yet denied him to be God. And two perſons being granted, it was now eaſie to prove the third, which Mr. <hi>Gunning</hi> laboured in by ſetting forth the divine reaſon of the Trinity of Perſons in the Unity of the Eſſence.</p>
               <p>After theſe things he ſeemed to be left without reply or contradiction in a ſort, and therefore was earneſtly ſollicited to be baptized, by urging the command of Chriſt for that purpoſe, which he ſeemed not to deny, but was held off by delays, and ſome reluctancies of ſpirit, which we endeavored to remove by ſhewing him the great danger that hung over him, if he ſhould refuſe to yield to thoſe convictions that were upon him, and urged the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of divers in the Scriptures that were ſpeedily baptized upon their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. At laſt he was perſwaded, ſo as with great earneſtneſs to deſire it, as hath been before declared. And now
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:106523:82"/>nothing remained but to prepare him for the bleſſed work of his ſolemn admiſſion into the Chriſtian Church. To which purpoſe he was committed to me at <hi>Chel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey</hi> for his inſtruction, and that he might be commended to God in prayer, with the help of Mr. <hi>Samois,</hi> who did the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of an Interpreter; amongſt other diſcourſes I had with him, I preſſed him hard to look to his ſincerity, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him that if he ſhould deal falſly with God, he might provoke him to great judgments. And I drew up an Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Apoſtles Creed for him, which I intend, if it ſhall be thought fit, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh for the good of him and others.</p>
               <p>Upon the Friday before the Lords Day, on which he was to be baptiſed, I brought him into Mr. <hi>Gunnings</hi> Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at <hi>Exceſter-houſe,</hi> and after that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered him unto him for ſome further pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of him. When the day came, and the holy and ſolemn buſineſs of his Baptiſm was to be performed in <hi>Exceſter</hi> houſe Chappel, (I having been before this work of converſion turned out of my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the Pariſh Church of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> upon the occaſion of my being ſo bold as to give the Congregation and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-men
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:106523:82"/>a Sermon in the Abby, where after two <hi>Pſalms</hi> ſung out in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of a Miniſter, none came to ſupply the place that I ſaw or knew of) a full and chearful Congregation being there aſſembled, Mr. <hi>Gunning</hi> officiated; and after the firſt part of the Service ended, the Convert came in in his Turk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Habit; and at his enterance into the Congregation deſired ſeveral times that he might be admitted to the Baptiſm of the Chriſtian Church, which being grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and theſe honorable and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy perſons, the young Counteſs of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> the Lord <hi>Gorge,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Philip Warwick,</hi> being Witneſſes at his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
               <p>He having made confeſſion of the Chriſtian faith in the Apoſtles Creed; and having anſwered the queſtions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Chriſtian Covenant and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion for himſelf, which have been u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually anſwered by the Godfathers and Godmothers at the Baptiſm of Children, and being commended to Gods Grace and Mercy in the prayers of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, with ſuch alterations as were neceſſary for the extraordinary caſe, he being ſtripped of his Garment to his
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:106523:83"/>Waſte, received his Baptiſm upon his knees with great humility, and was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Philip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Baptiſm being performed, by Mr. <hi>Gunnings</hi> permiſſion, I preached upon the occaſion, and took my Text out of the Fifteenth Chapter of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> at the Seventh Verſe, being the words of our Saviour, <hi>I ſay unto you, that likewiſe joy ſhall be in Heaven for one ſinner that repenteth, more then for ninety and nine juſt perſons that need no repentance.</hi> Of which Sermon it may be there ſhall be a further account given hereafter. And if God and Angels rejoyce, ſurely it is the duty of all good Chriſtians to keep conſort with them, and by the loving and charitable entertainment of this our Convert, to give enconragement to others to come in unto Chriſts fold.</p>
               <p>In the afternoon of the ſame day he came in another Habit, after the Engliſh faſhion (which was charitably provided for him by reverend Doctor <hi>Bernard</hi> of <hi>Grayes-Inn</hi>) and then Mr. <hi>Gunning</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a learned Sermon upon <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 31. as it is in the Liturgy tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>The Morians land ſhall ſoon ſtretch ont her hands unto God.</hi> And ſo the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:106523:83"/>ſolemnity of that happy day was ended. Our new Convert having ſince declared that he found extraordinary joy and ſolace in his ſoul at the time of his Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>He for the preſent lives in <hi>Holborn,</hi> at the houſe of the honourable and vertuous Lady <hi>Hatter,</hi> and is I conceive much improved in the Chriſtian know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as appeared by a diſcourſe he had lately at <hi>Chelſey,</hi> and I hope will prove an eminent Chriſtian.</p>
               <closer>Glory to God on high, on earth peace, good will towards men.</closer>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſalm 45.4, 5, 6.</hi>
                        </bibl> And gird thee with thy ſword upon thy thigh, O thou moſt mighty: according to thy worſhip and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown.</p>
                     <p>Good luck have thou with thine honor: ride on becauſe of the word of truth, of meekneſs and righteouſneſs, and let thy right hand teach thee terrible things.</p>
                     <p>Thine arrows are very ſharp, and the people ſholl be ſubdued unto thee: even in the midſt among the Kings enemies.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal 67. verſ. 1.</hi>
                        </bibl> God be merciful unto us, and bleſs us: and ſhew us the light of his
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:106523:84"/>countenance, and be merciful unto us.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <hi>2.</hi> That thy way may be known upon earth: thy ſaving health among all nations.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <hi>3.</hi> Let the people praiſe thee, O God: yea, let all the people praiſe thee.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <hi>4.</hi> O let the nations rejoyce and be glad, for thou ſhalt judge the folks righteouſly: and govern the nations upon earth.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <hi>5.</hi> Let the people praiſe thee, O God, let all the people praiſe thee.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <hi>6.</hi> Then ſhall the earth bring forth her encreaſe: and God even our own God, ſhall give us his bleſſing.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <hi>7.</hi> God ſhall bleſs us: and all the ends of the world ſhall fear him.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Eccleſiaſticus 36. ver. 1.</hi>
                        </bibl> Have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, O Lord God of all things, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold us, and [ſhew us the light of thy mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.]</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <hi>2.</hi> And ſend thy fear among the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which ſeek not after thee, [that they may know that there is no God but thou, and that they may ſhew thy wonderous works.]</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <hi>3.</hi> Lift up thine hand upon the ſtrange nations, that they may ſee thy power.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <hi>4.</hi> As thou art ſanctified in us before them, ſo be thou magnified among them before us.</p>
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:106523:84"/>
                     <p n="5">
                        <hi>5.</hi> That they may know thee, as we know thee: for there is none other God but onely thou, O Lord.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <hi>6.</hi> Renew the ſigns, and change the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: ſhew the glory of thine hand, and thy right arm, that they may ſhew forth thy won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous acts.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <hi>8.</hi> Make the time ſhort: remember thine oath, that thy wonderous works may be praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>10.</hi> Smite in ſunder the head of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that be our enemies, and ſay, There is none other but we.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>11.</hi> Gather all the tribes of Jacob toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, [that they may know that there is none other God but onely thou, and that they may ſhew thy wonderous works] and inherit thou them as from the begining.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>12.</hi> O Lord, have mercy upon the people that is called by thy name, and upon Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, whom thou haſt likened to a firſt born ſon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>13.</hi> Oh, be merciful unto Jeruſalem the city of thy ſanctuary, the city of thy reſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>14.</hi> Fill Sion, that it may magnifie thine oracles, and fill thy people with thy glory.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>15.</hi> Give witneſs unto thoſe that thou haſt poſſeſſed from the beginning, and raiſe up the prophecies that have been ſhewed in thy name.</p>
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:106523:85"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>16.</hi> Reward them that wait for thee, that thy Prophets may be found faithful.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>17.</hi> O Lord, hear the prayers of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants according to the bleſſings of Aaron o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thy people, [and guide thou us in the way of righteouſneſs,] that all they which dwell upon the earth, may know that thou art the Lord, the eternal God.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:106523:85"/>
               <head>The Paradiſe of Mahomet, which he promifeth unto his Follewers.</head>
               <p>THey ſhall be, ſaith he, in a Paradiſe watered with fair and delicate Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, which ſhall run ſo clear as if they were melted Chriſtal.</p>
               <p>They ſhall reſt in the ſhade, or refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing coolneſs of beautiful trees, full of leaves and branches, which by their moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall cauſe a pleaſant tune.</p>
               <p>They ſhall eat of all manner of ſweet and pleaſant fruits in all ſeaſons, and ſhall be ſolaced with the chanting of Ten thouſand little Birds, which ſhall warble amongſt their branches; and this ſhall bemingled with the conſort of moſt har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious inſtruments, and of moſt melodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous voices.</p>
               <p>Their Robes ſhall be moſt magnificent, and triumphant, as of ſilk wrought with gold, and chaſed with the richeſt ſtones and pearls.</p>
               <p>They ſhall lye in Beds embroidered with gold, and hung the corners and Pillows
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:106523:86"/>with great Pearls, and the Curtains ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ineſtimable and innumerable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones.</p>
               <p>That every one ſhall have his marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous beautiful women, with their Breaſts wantonly ſwelling, and Eyes like jet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed in ſilver, whiter then ſnow, as big as good big eggs.</p>
               <p>That with theſe they ſhall feaſt every day, and uſe all manner of ſports and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations poſſible, and ſhall be ſerved in their Feaſts with fair and great veſſels of gold and chriſtal, which ſhall be ſet with moſt precious Jewels, and ſhall be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred unto by the hands of fair Boyes, more poliſhed then the pearls themſelves, and more ſweet then Amber-greece, or the moſt oderiferous Perfumes of <hi>Arabia, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Two Books of great eſteem amongſt the Turks, beſides the Alcoran.</head>
               <p>THe firſt hath the deſcription of the Voyage of Mahomet in Paradiſe by the guidance of the Angel <hi>Gabriel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He went, ſay they, into the firſt heaven, mounted upon <hi>Alborach,</hi> a Beaſt a little
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:106523:86"/>bigger then an Aſs, having the face of a man; and found that firſt Sphear was of fine Silver, and ſo thick as the ſpace that a Footman can run in Five hundered years. There he found an Angel as tall as the ſpace of the journey of a Thouſand years, with Seventy thouſand other Angels, every one of which had Seventy thouſand Heads, and every Head ſeventy thouſand Horns, every Horn ſeventy thouſand Knots; and from one Knot to another the ſpace of the jouruey of forty years: And every Head ſeventy thouſand Faces, and every Face ſeventy thouſand Mouthes, and every Mouth ſeventy thouſand Tongues, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Tongue ſpake a thouſand Languages, with which they praiſed God every day ſeventy thouſand times.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Heaven was made all of burniſht Gold, where he ſaw a great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of others greater then theſe, and amongſt them one that had his feet on the earth, and his head in the third Heaven.</p>
               <p>But all theſe were Pigmies to one that he found in the third Heaven, which was ſo monſtrouſly great that he held the world in the palm of his hand, and yet it hindered him not from ſhutting it.</p>
               <p>In the fourth Heaven, every one had
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:106523:87"/>ſeventy pair of Wings, in every Wing ſeventy thouſand feathers to flie with, and every feather ſeventy thouſand cubits long.</p>
               <p>In the fifth Heaven the Angel that open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Gate to them had ſeven thouſand Arms, and every Arm ſeven thouſand Hands.</p>
               <p>In the other Heavens they found not any Angels of ſuch an unmeaſurable ſtature; but in the eighth Sphear, they toſſed the Globe of the Earth and Sea as eaſily as a little Ball.</p>
               <p>In the other Book is recited the Hiſtory of a diſcourſe between a Turk and a Jew, who asked him concerning the principal points of his Doctrine; he ſaid that God created a Paper, and a Pen of ſo fair a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, that the Pen was Five hundred days journey long, and Fourſcore thick; and that with this Pen that hath Fourſcore points or nebs is written perpetually all that hath been is or ſhall be in the world.</p>
               <p>That the Sun and Moon had equal light in the beginning, ſo that the day and night could not well be deſtinguiſhed; but that the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> flying put the end of his wing into the Moon, and made her loſe half her light.</p>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:106523:87"/>
               <p>There is mention made of a Cow that had forty horns, and between two of her horns the ſpace of a thouſand years jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and yet that this Cow was under the earth.</p>
               <p>Of a Fiſh that had his Head in the Eaſt, and the Tail in the Weſt, that beareth upon his back the Earth, the Sea, and the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</p>
               <p>That Rats were begotten in the Ark, of the ſneezing of a Sow or Boar; and Cats of the ſneezing of a Lion.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Seraphiel</hi> in the day of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection ſhall ſound a Trumpet Five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years journey long, and that then all the ſouls of the dead ſhall ſeek out their bodies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That the Mahometan Religion cannot be a true Religion.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. NO new Religion can be a true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</item>
                  <item>2. No cruel and bloody Religion can be a true Religion.</item>
                  <item>3. That Religion that hath no teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from heaven, but is grounded meerly upon the invention and authority of man, cannot be a true Religion.</item>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:106523:88"/>
                  <item>4. That Religion that contradicteth it ſelf, and thoſe authorities which it approve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and alloweth, cannot be a true Religion.</item>
                  <item>5. That Religion that affordeth no reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for ſin, no ſatisfaction to the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, nor any certain way to ſalvation, cannot be a true Religion.</item>
                  <item>6. That Religion that ſetteth not down a perfect Rule of holineſs and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, cannot be a true Religion.</item>
                  <item>7. That Religion that countenanceth and alloweth impurity, cannot be a true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</item>
                  <item>8. That Religion that is carried on not by ſpiritual but worldly and carnal ways, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a true Religion.</item>
                  <item>9. That Religion that propoſeth a felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſiſting in carnal and impure delights, cannot be a true Religion.</item>
                  <item>10. That Religion that confoundeth the difference between righteouſneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, cannot be a true Religion.</item>
                  <item>11 That Religion that diſchargeth from the prudent uſe of the means of ſafety and bleſſing, and teacheth people to tempt the Lord, cannot be a true Religion.</item>
                  <item>12. That Religion that propoſeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to violence and unrighteouſneſs, cannot be a true Religion.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106523:88"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
